<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The letters patents of the presbyterie vvith the plea and fruits of the prelacie. Manifested out of the scriptures, fathers, ecclesiasticall histories, Papists, and sundrie other authors. By Iames Peregrin.</title>
            <author>[Peregin, James].</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1632</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09313</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19622B.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103890</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839632</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839632</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4072</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09313)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4072)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1326:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The letters patents of the presbyterie vvith the plea and fruits of the prelacie. Manifested out of the scriptures, fathers, ecclesiasticall histories, Papists, and sundrie other authors. By Iames Peregrin.</title>
                  <author>[Peregin, James].</author>
                  <author>Partridge, James, attributed name. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 55, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Printed abroad :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed, MDCXXXII. [1632]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Formerly attributed to James Partridge. Quite probable that Peregrin is a pseudonym.</note>
                  <note>"Printed abroad."--STC.</note>
                  <note>Errata on verso of H2, final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 19420.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 19420 on UMI microfilm reel 1326.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Bishops --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Episcopacy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4072:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4072:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LETTERS PATENTS OF THE PRESBYTERIE: VVith THE PLEA AND FRVITS OF THE PRELACIE.</p>
            <p>Manifeſted out of the Scriptures, Fathers, Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories, Papiſts, and ſundrie other Authors.</p>
            <p>By Iames Peregrin.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>LVK. 16.14.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>All theſe things alſo heard the Phariſes, vvho vvere coueteous, and they derided him.</p>
               <p>And he ſaid vnto them, ye are they vvhich iuſtifie your ſelues before men, but God knoweth your hearts: for that vvhich is highly esteemed amongst men is abomination in the ſight of God.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed, MDCXXXII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:4072:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the ſacred honour of the Lord God, Creator of all things, and Iudge of all men.</head>
            <p>ALmightie and euerlaſting God, vvho haſt ſet thy king vpon thy holy hill of Sion, &amp; giuen him a kingdom that all nations, and languages ſhould <hi>ſerue</hi> him, a kingdom that ſhall haue no ende; giue vs vvee beſeech thee to knovv vvhat it is to haue him for the Chriſt, the only King and Lavvgiuer of his church, the <hi>Anointing</hi> that thou haſt giuen vs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to ſee that vvee haue, <hi>no neede that any man teach vs, but as the ſame anointing teacheth vs of all things,</hi> by himſelfe, and by his Apoſtles, and Prophets. O teach vs at laſt to <hi>abide in him,</hi> as <hi>he</hi> hath taught <hi>vs,</hi> that <hi>vvhen he ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, vvee may not be aſhamed before him at his comming.</hi> Thou only, O Lord, canſt beſt iudge vvhat are the things that truly belong to his kingdom and gouerument, vvhat ſubordinate officers thou haſt giuen to guide thy church, and vvho are Intruders and vſurpers: vvho ſerue aright to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thy Truth and gouernment, and vvho to obſcure and oppreſſe the ſame: vvho ſerue thy kingdom in a right vvay, &amp; vvho only pretend it, not ſeruing thee the Lord, <hi>but theire owne bellies.</hi> To vvhome then, but to thee, O dreadfull God, ſhould I thy poore ſeruant dedicate theſe his vveake labours? For thou, o Lord God, beſt knoweſt the work that thou haſt vvrought in thine, thou art beſt able to trie, and teach others to trie <hi>the Spirits vvhether they be of God, or noe:</hi> thou <hi>ſeareheſt the heart &amp; the reines,</hi> the end and ſcoape of euery mans vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings, vvho are led by <hi>thy Spirit into all Truth,</hi> and vvho are only lifted vp in an opinion thereof: vvho finding thy guidance in ſome things, preſume that thou teacheſt them all vvhich they beleeue, or to vvhich they are conformable, and doe not rather thinke it better to beleeue all that thou tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſt, to be conformed to that, and be reformed by it: vvho haue thy Truth in reſpect of the perſons, authoritie and
<pb facs="tcp:4072:2"/>benefits of men, and vvho in reſpect of thee alone, the only fountaine of Truth. Thou, o God, the righteous Iudge, ſeeſt vvhether I haue collected theſe proofes &amp; obſeruations for the cauſe of Chriſt alone, or for ſiniſter reſpects; thou beſt knovveſt thy ovvne Truth, and art beſt able to defend it, and all them that ſeeke it. Princes are men: ſuch as truſt to much to theire iudgment and protection, do oft finde themſelues revvarded accordingly: Thou haſt the hearts of kings, and all other men, in thy hand, thou canſt turne them to ſee and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knovvledge thy truth. Thou only, that <hi>makest light to ſhine out of darknes,</hi> canſt <hi>ſhine in theire hearts, to giue them true knovvledge</hi> and obedience. Other Patrons can a litle counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance a booke vvith their greate names &amp; favours: but thou, o Kings of kings haſt <hi>a name aboue all names:</hi> thou only canſt <hi>perſvvade Iapheth to dvvell in the tents of Shem.</hi> Thou only canſt informe and aſſure the heart in thy ovvne Truth. VVho is able to hinder the light thereof, vvhen thou vvilt haue it knovvne &amp; acknovvledged? O therefore <hi>be mercifull vnto vs,</hi> &amp; <hi>cauſe the light of thy countenance to ſhine vpon vs, that thy vvay may be knovvne vpon earth, &amp; thy ſauing health vnto all nations;</hi> that they may ſee the things that belong vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their peace, leaſt haueing them hid from theire eies, they <hi>groape at noone day, ſtraine at a gnat &amp; ſwallow a Camel.</hi> Thou art the greate God that vvilt take account of euerie mans vvorkes, and bring euerie ſecret vvorke, and counſeil vnto light. It is thy grace and protection that I ſtand in neede of. O be vvith me, and forſake me not, but ſhevv thy might in my vveakenes. This g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ace &amp; vvhat elſe thou knovveſt neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for me, the Reader, or any of thy afflicted people, grant vnto vs all for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, the Sonne of thy loue, to vvhome vvith thee, and thy holy Spirit, three perſons and one God, be aſcribed, as due is, all honour, might, maieſtie and dominion, novv and for euer.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4072:3"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>IF a man, Chriſtian Reader, liuing in Rome, Spaine, or any other kingdom, where the truth is in any point oppreſſed, ſhould to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince and conuert his nation, be deſirous to ſet out a booke on that ſubiect: he would eaſely conceiue, that by making himſelfe publick he ſhould nothing benefit the cauſe, he might fall and periſh in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition before three men could come to reade it: and that therefore it were better to liue obſcurely, and get it ſecretly printed and diſperſed: who could for this either blame him, or vnder nice pretences, reiect his proofes fairely deducted out of Gods word? So, if I, conſidering that I haue liued an obſcure life, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſmale and of no reputation, that in this caſe to make my ſelf publick would doe no good, but rather raiſe againſt me many mightie and vndeſerued ennemies, &amp; get my labour in Chriſts, cauſe the ſooner ſuppreſſed, haue therfore tooke a like priuate courſe, to the ende that Gods Truth might finde the more vnpreuentible paſſage: thinke not, that it will excuſe any man, to ſay of me, he is a libeller, or as the Phariſes did of our Lord and Sauiour, <hi>As for this fellow vvee knovv not vvhence he is.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 9.29.33.</note> But if God, by ſo weake a meanes as I am, open thine eyes in a point of any conſequence, ſay rather of the poore ſeruant, as the man borne blinde of the Lord and maiſter, <hi>If this man vvere not of God, he could doe nothing.</hi> Let me not be reckoned an<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>enemie</hi> for manifeſting Gods truth: but remember that herein thou ſheweſt thy<note n="*" place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.3</note> 
               <hi>loue</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> if his doctrine, <hi>his commandements be not grieuous vnto thee</hi> For his ſake therefore reade this ſmale treatiſes and hereby thou maieſt ſee a reaſon, why many learned miniſters do not or will not know or regard the truth in this point: why the moſt in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land are ſo vnwilling to know any thing thereof, ſeaſt it ſhould hinder them from ſubſcribing, and hauing of a good liuing, or cauſe them to be put to ſilence, if they ſhould either preach, write, or ſpeake againſt the gouernment of the Biſhops.</p>
            <p>If I haue proued that it makes greatly to the ſaluation of the Church, and the preſeruing of the faith it ſelfe, in that puritie and ſimpliciue, wherein it was left vnto vs by the Apoſtles and Prophets, that the Truth of God, be well knowne and manifeſted, in this point: remember it is thy duty, not to haue that bleſſed Truth <hi>vvith reſpect of perſons:</hi> but in a right receiuing of it,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.1.</note> to <hi>Kiſſe the Sonne least he be angrie,</hi> and euen to crie mightely to God,<note place="margin">Pſa. 2.</note> to reforme that Church, by whoſe power, any part of his Teſtament, lies darkened vnder a corrupt gloſſe, or being cleered, is forced to ſeeke corners. And thus hopeing that God will raiſe vp many friends to his owne cauſe, and giue them hearts to vſe all ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt wiſdom and dilligence in ſuch a caſe, I reſt <hi>Thine in Chriſt Ieſus</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iames Peregrin.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4072:3"/>
            <head>THE LETTERS PATENTS OF THE PRESBYTERIE, VVith the Plea and fruites of the Prelacie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>An, fallen in Adam, going after his ovvne vnderſtanding in ſpirituall things, vvalketh on in darknes, and oft thinketh himſelfe in the right vvay, vvhen he erreth &amp; knovveth not vvhether he goeth: vvherein vvho is many times mort blinde in ſom things, then he that thinks himſelfe <hi>perfit, a Scribe,</hi> and a meſſenger fit for the kingdome of God? vvherefore our Sauiour thanketh his Father, that <hi>he had hid theſe things from this vviſe &amp; learned,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 1. Cor. 1.20.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; reuealed them to babes.</hi> And the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>vvhere is the vviſe? vvhere is the Scribe? vvhere is the diſputer of this vvorld? Hath not God made fooliſh the vviſdom of this vvorld?</hi> But leaſt ſom man might here ſay, If this be oft the caſe of Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins, Doctours and Guides, vvhat ſhall become of their poore Diſciples? If the Shepheards erre, the ſheepe muſt needes vvander, and be in a vvorſe eſtate: the Lord in his greate mercie promiſed,<note place="margin">Ioel 2.28. Iſa. 44.3. Chap. 42.16. 1. Cor. 1.27.</note> that he vvould povvre <hi>out of his ſpirit vpon all fleſh, vpon theirs ſeede</hi> and ofſpring: and make <hi>the blinde to ſee.</hi> VVhich he ſo fully performed, as to <hi>chooſe to fooliſh things of the vvorld to confound the vviſe.</hi> And yet becauſe many vvould pretend the Spirit that mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt litle, but ſom fevv vvell knowne principles, &amp; the viſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their ovvne heart, and that they vvreſt the Scriptures to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme it, he bids his people <hi>trie the ſpirits,</hi> and addeth, theſe gracious promiſes, fulfilled in the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Ier. 31.34.</note> 
               <hi>They ſhall all know
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4072:4"/>me from the least of them to the greatest of them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.16.</note> 
               <hi>The ſpirituall man diſcerneth all things.</hi> Neuerthele<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to ſhevv they ſhould come to it by a Rule, he had ſaid, <hi>A law ſhall proceede from me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 51.4.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; I vvill make my iudgment to rest for a light of the people, mine armes ſhall iudge the people.</hi>
               <note place="margin">chap. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>The Iles ſhall vvaite upon me, and on mine Arme ſhall they trust.</hi> That is on my vvord. For the Prophets had ſaid,<note place="margin">Mich. 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>The Lavv ſhall goe forth of Sion, and the vvord of the Lord out of Ieruſalem, And he ſhall iudge amonge the nations:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.15.16.</note> euen in this vvorld: The reuealed vvord is ſufficient in all matters of faith and ſaluation, <hi>For doctrine reproofe, and instruction, that the man of God may be perfit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The holy Ghoſt teacheth that vvhich Chriſt hath ſpoken,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.</note> and no other doctrine, for ſaith our Lord, <hi>He ſhall not ſpeake of himſelfe, but vvhatſoeuer he ſhall heare, that ſhall he ſpeake, and he vvill ſhew you things to come</hi> (as the things in the Reuelation,<note place="margin">Reuel. 4.1.</note> that ſome ſhall <hi>depart from the faith,</hi> &amp; the like.) <hi>He ſhall take of mine and ſhew unto you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh 15.15.</note> For he had ſaid, <hi>All things that I haue heard of my Father, I haue made knowne</hi> vnto you:<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 20.27.</note> therefore the holy Ghoſt brought all theſe to their remembrance: and they haue <hi>declared to vs all that councell of God.</hi> That vvhich is vvritten, is that vvhich Chriſt hath ſpoken to them,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.3.</note> as Iohn ſaith, <hi>That vvhich vvee haue ſeene and heard declare vvee unto you,</hi> that is to ſay in theſe our vvritings, <hi>that ye alſo may haue fellovſhip vvith vs,</hi> that is in the knovvledge of theſe things, and truly <hi>our fellovvſhip is vvith the Father and vvith his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> that is in knovving the<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.16.</note> minde of God. He excepteth nothing reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, vvhether it be aboute the conuerſion and perſeuerance of the Saints, or Predeſtination it ſelfe, ſo far as it is reuealed in the Scripture. This vvord is an<note n="*" place="margin">Cant. 3.4. Pſa. 45.1.</note> 
               <hi>ointment powred out.</hi> It miniſtreth grace in them that art his. <hi>Grace vvas powred into his lips:</hi> and ſaith Iohn, <hi>ye neede not that any man teach you, but
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4072:4"/>as the ſame anointing teacheth you of all things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.27.</note> 
               <hi>and is truth and is no lie:</hi> VVhich I vvill no further vrge againſt the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvritten verities, preſumptions, errours and blaſphemies of the Church of Rome. For he, vvho is the vvord, ſaith, <hi>I am the light of the vvorld he that followeth me ſhall not vvalke in in darkneſſe, but ſhall haue the light of life.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.12.</note> And this is not only meant of Apoſtles and Doctors, but of euerie true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuer, as he ſaith, <hi>I am come a light</hi> into the vvorld,<note place="margin">chap. 12.46.40.</note> that <hi>vvhoſoeuer beleeueth on me ſhould not abide in darkneſſe.</hi> And to ſhevv vs that in all matters of faith vvee ought to be iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the reuealed vvord novv, ſince vvee muſt, vvhether vvee vvill or no, be iudged by it at the laſt day, he addeth, <hi>He that reiecteth me, and receiueth not my vvords, hath one that iudgeth him: the vvord that I haue ſpoken, he ſhall iudge him</hi> in the laſt day. Certaine it is, that Chriſt as he is the eteernall vvord manifeſted and preached, is the only Iudge and Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his church in matters of faith &amp; ſaluation: therefore it is ſaid to him, <hi>Rule thou in the midſt of thine enemies.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 110.</note> The kingdome,<note place="margin">Dan. 7.14.</note> and dominion <hi>vnder the vvhole heauen</hi> is giuen to him, vvho is <hi>the Arme of God that ſhould rule for him.</hi> God <hi>ruleth by his power for euer,</hi> that is by his vvord;<note place="margin">Iſa. 40.10.</note> of vvhome is ſaide, <hi>I vvill giue thee</hi> for a couenant of the people,<note place="margin">Pſa. 66.2.</note> 
               <hi>for a light of the Gentiles. I haue ſet my King upon my holy hill of Sion. He ſhall reigne ouer the Houſe of Iacob for euer.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 1.33.</note>
            </p>
            <p>BVt becauſe hereticks, and prophane and vnruly perſons, vvould ariſe in the church: &amp; there muſt needes be ſome orders &amp; officers in the church, before vvhom ſuch might be conue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, &amp; by whoſe paines in alleadging the ſcriptures, they might be conuinced, reformed &amp; ordered:<note place="margin">Act. 20.</note> he ordained ſom to be ouerſeers of the flock, that ſhould <hi>not be nouices,</hi> but vvell gronded in the faith,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.6</note> 
               <hi>to hold faſt the faithfull word as they haue bene taught,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>that they may be able by ſound doctrin both to exhort
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4072:5"/>and conuince the gainſayers.</hi> VVhich vvhile they faithfully doe, vvithout preſſing for doctrines the commandements of men: it is not ſo much, they that rule, as Chriſt the vvord that ruleth in them:<note place="margin">Iſaie 9.6. chap. 11.4.</note> therefore it is ſaid: <hi>The gouernment ſhall be vpon his ſhoulders. He ſhall ſmite the earth vvith the rod of of his mouth.</hi> And ſo they are ſubordinate Shepheards and Biſhops to feed the flock, to keepe and reduce the ſheepe vnto the obedience of the <hi>chiefe Shepheard &amp; Biſhop of theire ſoules,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.25 chap. 5.4.</note> vvhich is Chriſt. In regard vvhereof, <hi>the vveapons of theire vvarfare are not carnall, but mightie through God, to the pulling downe of ſtrong holds,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 10.4</note> 
               <hi>caſting downe imaginations, and euerie high thought, that exalteth it ſelfe againſt the knowledge of God, and bringing into captiuitie euery thought to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The greateſt queſtion is aboute the dignitie, iuriſdiction, povver and authoritie of theſe Officers, and eſpecially of the office of a Biſhop: vvhether by Gods Teſtament, and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance it be to ſuperintend ouer other Paſtors and Elders in a dioceſſe or Prouince: or, as others affirme, Paſtoral, ouer one flocke and congregation, vvherein he is an Elder, and vvith other Elders an ouerſeer of the ſame. In vvhich controuerſie, men, that are not vvillingly ignorant, or vvilfully obſtinate and blind, may receiue full ſatisfaction by the cleere teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Scripture, and conſent of the Fathers, ſhevving vs the old and good vvay that all ſhould ſeeke &amp; follow. VVhereas he that commeth vvith a ſcoffing, or preuidicate cenſure, <hi>ſpeaking euill of the things he knowes not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude 10. Pro. 3.22. Pro. 14.6. Pſa. 25.14.</note> 
               <hi>or in frowardnes will not know,</hi> can not ſo eaſily diſcerne the Truth. <hi>Aſcorner ſeeketh vviſdome, and findeth it not, but knowledge is eaſy to him that vvill vnderſtand, The ſecret of the lord is vvith them that feare him, and he vvill ſhew them his couenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVhen Paul the Apoſtle of the Gentiles had firſt preached the Goſpell in diuers of their cities, he &amp; Barnabas retourned
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4072:5"/>againe to Lyſtra, &amp; to Iconium, and Antioch,<note place="margin">Act. 13. chap. 14.21.22.23.</note> 
               <hi>to confirme the ſoules of the Diſciples,</hi> &amp; exhort them to <hi>continue</hi> in the faith: &amp; then it is ſaid expreſly, <hi>They ordained them Elders in euerie church by election.</hi> The vvord in the Greeke is <hi>Preſbuterois</hi> Preſbyters or Elders. Of it comes the Latin vvord Preſbyter, vvhich ſignifies an Elder: and vvhich, as all confeſſe, in the primatiue ages of the church, was giuen (if not to ſom others, yet at leaſt) to euerie ordinarie Paſtor, of euerie congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in regard, that he, vvatched ouer the flock, to keepe them ſound in the ſaith, and holy in life and manners. In place of thoſe that men call parſons, or Curates of ſeuerall Pariſhes, there vvere then preſbiters of ſeuerall congregations.<note place="margin">Nicod. Dictionar. French and Latin.</note> Our vvord preiſt ſeemes to come from the French vvord <hi>Preſtre</hi> a preiſt, vvhich, as Nicod obſerueth, properlie ſignifies an Elder or preſbiter: though after the maſſe vvas vnderſtood to be a Sacrifice, offered by the hand of preſbiters, the name preſtre or preiſt remained, but vvas alſo corruptly applied to a Sacrificer or Maſſe preiſt, &amp; in time vvas only taken in that ſenſe both in France, and elſvvhere. VVherein vve may an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvvere vvith our Sauiour, from the beginning, it vvas not ſo; but a Preiſt, that was a Preſbiter or Elder: therfore throughout the vvhole booke of God, vvhere there is any ſpeech of thoſe orders of Aarons Sons, that vvaited at the Altar, the french Proteſtants do not in their Bibles tranſlate it preiſt, but Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificer: &amp; blame vs that vvee do not the like, to diſtinguiſh them &amp; all maſſe mongers from the preſbiters or prieſts or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained in the nevv Teſtament. Indeede Reuel. 1. Chriſt is ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>de to make vs kings &amp; <hi>Hiereis, Sacrificers,</hi> vvhere you haue the ſame vvord that in the Septuagint, and in the Goſpell is put for the Ievviſh Sacricificers: but this is by Iohn myſtical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie applied to all true Chriſtians, and is not here <hi>Preſbuterois,</hi> Preſbiters, but a vvord far different, and therefore can not be vnderſtood of the office, and miniſtrie of the Preſbyters
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4072:6"/>ordained by the Apoſtles. In the nevv Teſtament mention is oft made of theſe Preſbyters or Elders.<note place="margin">Act. 15.2.4.6.</note> Paul, Barnabas, and others vvere ſent to Ieruſalem <hi>vnto the Apoſtles, and Elders:</hi> vvhen they came thither.<note place="margin">verſ. 22.</note> 
               <hi>They vvere receiued of the church, and of the Apostles and Elders. And the Apoſtles, and Elders came together,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 16.4.</note> 
               <hi>to conſider of this matter. Then it pleaſed the Apostles, and Elders, vvith the vvhole church. And vvrote let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, The Apostles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">chap. 10.17.18. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>and Elders, and brethren ſend greeting. They deliuered them, the decrees that vvere ordained of the Apostles, and Elders. From Miletus he ſent to Epheſus, &amp; called the Elders of the church:</hi> and ſaid vnto them, <hi>ye know from the firſt daie that I came into Aſia &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 28.</note> 
               <hi>Take heede therefore vnto your ſelues, and to all the flock ouer vvhich the holy Ghost hath made you Biſhops, to feede the church of God.</hi> The new tranſlation reads it <hi>Ouerſeers,</hi> but the vvord is <hi>Epiſcopus,</hi> Biſhops, the ſame, that is vſed 1. Tim. 3. <hi>A Biſhop muſt be blameleſſe &amp;c.</hi> Indeede both there, and here it may be tranſlated a Biſhop, or an Ouerſeer. For in the original, as a Preſbiter is an Elder, ſo a Biſhop is an Ouerſeer. But marke he ſaith to the Preſbyters, <hi>Take heede to all the flock ouer vvhich the holy Ghost hath made you Biſhops</hi> to feede, &amp;c. VVhence it is infalliblie plaine 1. That the Preſbiterall gouernment is the expreſſe ordinance of the holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.</note> 
               <hi>vvho changeth</hi> not: and of vvhome Chriſt ſaith, <hi>He ſhall not ſpeake of himſelfe: for he ſhall take of mine &amp; ſhew vnto you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13.</note> Novv Chriſt <hi>is yeſterdaie, and to daie, and the ſame alſo for euer.</hi> This ordinance is therefore vnalterable. 2. That Elders by Chriſts ordinance are, or ought to be, ouer euery congregation. Take heede to <hi>all the flock</hi> ouer vvhich the holy Ghoſt hath made you Biſhops.<note place="margin">Act 14 23</note> So Paul and Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas <hi>ordained them Elders in euerie church</hi> by election, &amp; Paul ſaith to Titus, <hi>I left thee in Creete, to ſet in order the things that are vvanting,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. ordaine Elders in euerie citie, as I had appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thee.</hi> For a vvhole prouince, or dioceſſe is to greate a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4072:6"/>flock for one man, he can not take heede to all the flock, as the Elders of one church may.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That their office is to feede the flock, &amp; church of God, vvhich one man can not doe in a vvhole Dioceſſe, &amp; vvhen they haue occaſion to binde or looſe, to reproue, correct, or comfort, to excommunicate, or reſtore, that muſt alſo be by the vvord: for it is he that in iuſt cauſes giues them authority, themſelues are not <hi>Lords of Gods heritage,</hi> as S Peter ſaith,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.3</note> to doe it at their ovvne pleaſure, by their ovvne rules, and tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 5.4</note> 
               <hi>vvith the power of Christ.</hi> For he <hi>ſmites the earth, vvith the rod of his mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That the holy Ghoſt hath made the Preſbiters Biſhops ouer the flock. For the vvords are peremptorie, Take heede to your ſelues, &amp; to all the flock, ouer vvhich the holy Ghoſt hath made you Biſhops: there vvere diuers Elders of the church of pheſus &amp; the places that bordered neer it, as of that of Philippi, or Ieruſalem act. 21.18. to them all Paul ſaith, The holy Ghoſt hath made you biſhops, to feede the church, So Phil. 1. To all the ſaints vvhich are at Philippi vvith the Biſhops &amp; Deacons: that is, vvith the Elders, preſbiters,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.1.</note> and deacons: for ye ſee the preſbiters are biſhops: or othervviſe you muſt graunt, that there vvere more biſhops then one in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> citie: therefore Theodore vvell vnderſtands it of the preſbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: vvhich Bellarmine, obſeruing can not denie,<note place="margin">Bellar. de Clericis l 4 c. 14. Tit. 1.5.6.7.</note> but that here alſo preſbiters are called Biſhops. VVhich is yet more cleere by that to Titus, <hi>I left thee in Creete, that thou ſhouldeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>daine preſbiters in euerie citie, if any be blameleſſe, the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band of one vvife, haueing faithfull children not accuſed of riot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r vnrulie for a biſhop,</hi> (that is the Preſbiter before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) <hi>muſt be blameleſſe, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vbi ſupra.</note> All vvhich places are ſo cleare that Bellarmine confeſſeth, that in them all the preſbiters are called Biſhops, &amp; conſequently, that the Trent fathers cried, vvho vvould proue, that Dioceſſan Biſhops are inſtituted by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4072:7"/>Chriſt and ſuperiour to Preſbyters <hi>iure diuino,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſtor. of the councel of Trent. pag. 597. 598. en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh.</note> becauſe Paul ſaith, <hi>Take heede to all the flock ouer vvhich the holy Ghoſt hath made you Biſhops:</hi> vvhich by his ovvne confeſſion is ſpoken to Preſbyters: therefore he anſvvers to all the three places verrie poorely, <hi>that in thoſe daies, theſe names Biſhop &amp; Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter vvere common to all preists,</hi> as if Phil. 1. vvith the Biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops and deacons, the ſenſe muſt be thus, <hi>VVith the Preiſts &amp; theire miniſters the deacons:</hi> vvhich is a vveake ſhift of a Ieſuit and ſo learned a Cardinal. For did the Apoſtle call the preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, Biſhops in all theſe three places, &amp; ſay the holy Ghoſt had made them Biſhops ouer the flocke, &amp; yet are they not ſo? And if it vvere then a name ſo common to all preiſts, why ſhould it novv be thus reſtrained to one in a countie or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince? and he accounted an heretick, that vvith the holy Ghoſt affirmeth, the preſbiters to be Biſhops, as in theſe three places?</p>
            <p>And therefore out of all doubt,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.</note> vvhen Paul ſaith, <hi>If any man deſire the office of a Biſhop, he deſireth a good vvorke, &amp;c.</hi> That is the office of a preſbiter or Elder, vvho is a Biſhop, &amp; that ſo he addeth, <hi>Theſe things vvrite</hi> I <hi>unto thee, that thou mightest know how thou</hi> (a Biſhop or preſbiter) <hi>oughtest to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue thy ſelfe.</hi> Othervviſe he vvould not haue paſſed, as he doth from the duty of a Biſhop to the duty of a deacon: but rather firſt from the duty of a Biſhop to the duty of a preſbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or paſtor, that is, if it had not beene one and the fame of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, ſomtime ſet forth vnder the name of an Elder or preſbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,<note place="margin">Tit. 1.5.6.7.</note> &amp; ſomtime of a Biſhop, as in that to Titus before allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged (vvhich ſhevves vs that vvhen it is ſaid of Titus, that he vvas <hi>ordained the first Biſhop of the Cretians,</hi> that muſt needes be the firſt preſbiter,<note place="margin">Chriſoſt. in 1. Tim. 3.</note> &amp; ſo Timothie. (2. Tim. in fin.) vvhich in effect is acknovvledged by <hi>Chryſoſ.</hi> in his Comentarie on that chapter to Timothie, vvho, though he liued in a time vvhen canons, cuſtom, and cloaked ambition had made a litle
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4072:7"/>difference, ſaith, <hi>There is almoſt no difference betweene a Biſhop and a preſbyter, ſeeing the care of the church is alſo graunted to the preſbyters: ſurely by giuing of orders only they are their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours, &amp; herein they only ſeeme to be more then the preſbiters.</hi> Bellarmin acknovvledgeth that Primaſius,<note place="margin">Bellar. de clerìcis, l. 4. c. 14.</note> Theophilact and Oecumenius, in their Comentaries vpon the ſame place do teach the ſame thing, &amp; almoſt in the ſame vvords. VVherin they come but litle ſhort of that, vvhich is more plainly affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by Hierom, on the firſt of Titus.<note place="margin">Hieron. in Tit. 1.</note> 
               <hi>A preſbiter and a Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>op is one and the ſame thing: and before by the inſtinct of the deuil, factions vvere made in religion, and it vvas ſaid among the people:</hi> I <hi>am of Paul,</hi> I <hi>of Apollo &amp;</hi> I <hi>of Cephas, the churches vvere gouerned by the common conſent of the preſbiters: but after euery one thought thoſe which he had baptiſed to be his, not Christs, it vvas ordained in all the vvorld, that one choſen from among the preſbiters ſhould be ſet ouer the reſt, unto vvhome all the care of the church ſhould pertaine, and the ſeedes of Sbhiſmes ſhould be taken away.</hi> And a litle lovver. As <hi>therfore preſbiters know themſelues to be ſubiect by the cuſtome of the church to him that is ſet ouer them, ſo let the Biſhops know, it is rather by the custom of the church, then by any diſpoſition of the diuine truth, that they are greater then the preſbiters, and that the church ought to be gouerned in commune.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vbi ſupra.</note> Bellarmin doth not only cite theſe places thus, but confeſſeth farther that Hiero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. hath the like things in his 85. Epiſtle to Euagrius. Yet he vvould faine haue it thought that Hiero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. held a Biſhop to be greater then a preſbiter <hi>iure diuino:</hi> contenting himſelfe, for lack of a better, to take that for a ſufficient proofe, vvhere he ſaith to Euagrius, <hi>vvhat doth the Biſhop, giueing of orders excepted, vvhich the preſbiter may not alſo doe?</hi> vvhereas indeede this doth rather proue the contrarie, namely that preſbiters had deciſiue voices in councels, might excommunicate, or doe any thing elſe in their flocks, belonging to gouernment, ſaue
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4072:8"/>the giuing of orders, this beeing all the difference of povver and authority, the Biſhops had them gained.</p>
            <p>VVherein you muſt needes vnderſtand him as before, that it is rather by the cuſtome of the church, then any diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the diuine truth, that they vvere herein greater then the Elders: the ſame or the like humain ordinance &amp; cuſtom, vvhich reſtrained the title of a Biſhop to one in a Dioceſſe, vvhich before vvas common to all preſbiters, gaue him alſo the ſole povver of giuing of orders, vvhich before belonged to preſbiters in common,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.14.</note> as is cleere by that, <hi>Neglect not the gift that is in thee, vvhich vvas giuen thee by propheſie, vvith the laying on of the hands of the preſbiterie.</hi> Kemnitius there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth vvell obſerue here,<note place="margin">Vbi ſupra.</note> that a Biſhop may be ordained by Preſbiters, therefore there is no difference betweene a Biſhop and a preſbiter. Bellarmin hereat offended anſvvers vvith the Greekes verie vveakely, <hi>By the preſbiterall name, they vnderſtood the quire or companie of the preſbiters, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Biſhops, vvhich laide their hands on the new biſhop.</hi> They that laied their hands on him vvere preſbiters, but that is (ſay Bellarmin and others) Biſhops. So ſaith S. Paul, and ſo ſay vvee, preſbiters are biſhops. Indeed Bellarmin and the Greekes, do rather meane the biſhops vvere preſbiters; but it is as true the preſbiters are biſhops, and that the loue of proffit or preeminence, or mens care to ſaue the honour of their church, and cuſtoms, haue blinded many, that they can not ſee a thing ſo cleere, that by impoſition of hands of the preſbiterie, he was made a preſbiter, that is a biſhop. VVhere vvee muſt vnderſtand, that they only laide their hands on thoſe that vvere choſen by voices or hands. For it is ſaid. <hi>They ordained them Elders by ſuffrages,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 14.23, Beza annot</note> as Beza obſerueth out of the Greeke vvord VVhich <hi>commeth from a custome of the Greeks, vvho gaue their ſuffrages, by holding vp their hands. And,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the force of this vvord Keirotoneſantes, is to be obſerued, that vvee may know, that Paul and Barnabas did nothing of a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4072:8"/>priuate vvill, neither excerciſed any tirannie in the church, like that vvhich is vſed by the Romiſh harlot,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem Annota. in 1. Tim. 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>or her pages, vvhich they call ordinaries.</hi> So as he ſhevveth, vvas <hi>the gift of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, giuen to Timothie vvith the laying on of the hands of the Preſbiters.</hi> And thus is that to be vnderſtood, <hi>lay hands ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainlie on noe man, &amp;c. that is doe not, vvhat in thee lieth, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainlie to admit any man to any Ecleſiaſticall fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ction,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem in cap. 5.22.</note> 
               <hi>for neither did all authoritie reſide in the power of Timothie alone, but the Election vvas made by the ſuffrages of the vvhole church, as vvee ſaid on</hi> Act. 14.23. <hi>and as is cleere by the election of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias, and of the deacons, &amp; lastlie by this that vvith the laying on of the hands of the Preſbiterie, the man choſen vvas conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to the Lord,</hi> as 1. Tim. 4.14.<note place="margin">Idem in Tit. 1.</note> By theſe places, as he ſhevveth, is that of Titus to be expounded, <hi>That thou ſhouldeſt ordaine them</hi> Elders, that is <hi>by ſuffrages,</hi> as Act. 14.23. <hi>by which place you may vnderstand vvhy he addeth,</hi> as had appointed thee, ſee alſo 1. Tim. 5.22. For <hi>in the choice of Mathias, nothing is carried by Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem in Act. 1.</note> 
               <hi>as by one endued with more excellent dignitie but by the ſuffrages of the vvhole church,</hi> there aſſembled: It is ſaid: They appointed tvvo. So for deacons the Apoſtles ſaid: <hi>Looke ye out among you ſeauen men, &amp;c.</hi> then it is added. <hi>And the ſaying pleaſed the vvhole multitude, And they choſe Steuen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 6.3.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. And ſet them before the Apoſtles, &amp; vvhen they had praied, they laid their hands on them.</hi> Therefore lay hands ſodainly on no man, that is till he be vvell, &amp; aduiſedly choſen, &amp; praiers be made vvith faſting. VVhich is ſpoken to all preſbiters in his perſon, &amp; eſpecially to himſelfe, as beeing both a preſbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; an Euangeliſt, which is greater. And thus indeede Paul left Titus to <hi>ordaine them preſbiters in euerie citie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1.5.7.</note> that is by ſuffrages, as he had done Act. 14.25. Othervviſe Titus ſhould ſeeme to haue had an office like that,<note place="margin">Hiſtor. of the counc. of Trent. pag. 611.</note> vvhich the papalins in Trent chalenged for the Pope, to be a biſhop of biſhops, that other biſhops ſhould receiue inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4072:9"/>For theſe preſbiters are called Biſhops verſ. 7. but this makes not Titus a preſbiter of preſbiters, that is a Biſhop of Biſhops, much leſſe doth it giue it to any other or infer that he muſt haue one to ſucceede him in ſuch office.</p>
            <p>It is obiected that Paul ſaith,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.19.</note> againſt a preſbiter, <hi>receiue not an accuſation, but before two or three vvitneſses.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Vbi ſupra</note> VVhere ſaith Bellarmin, vve ſee a Biſhop, in the <hi>time of the Apostles, the Iudge of the preſbiters: therefore their true prince &amp; ſuperiour.</hi> I anſvver this can not be 1.<note place="margin">Mat. 20.25</note> Becauſe Chriſt ſaith to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>ye know that the Prince of the Gentiles exerciſes dominion oner them, and they that are greate exerciſe authoritie upon them, But it ſhall not be ſo among you.</hi> And S. Peter ſaith to the preſbiters, <hi>take the ouerſight of the flock, not as beeing Lords ouer Gods</hi> heritage: much leſſe as Lords ouer other preſbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, for that vvere to make one a Biſhops of Biſhops, or the Pope of a prouince. 2. That Timothie vvas the firſt preſbiter or Biſhop in that church, and not only an Euangeliſt, vvhich is greater, but a man of exterordinarie gifts: therfore S. Paul vvrites to him an Elder, vvhat courſe he and all Elders are to take, if any of their number be accuſed before them, as he ſaith, <hi>that thou mightest knovv hovv to behaue thy ſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5. tim. 3.15</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c,</hi> For all the Elders vſed to meete in ſuch greate caſes: and oft times other brethren alſo of the congregation Act. 15.6.20.23. Paul ſaith to the Corinthians <hi>vvhen ye are gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. cor. 5.4.</note> 
               <hi>and my ſpirit vvith the power of our Lord Ieſus Christ,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18.17</note> 
               <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer ſuch a one unto Satan.</hi> In vvhich ſenſe Chriſt ſaith, <hi>If he ſhall neglect to heare tvvo or three, tell it to the church: but if he neglect to heare the church, let him be unto thee as a heathen.</hi> And Paul bids the preſbyters to take <hi>heede to themſelues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 20.</note> and to all the flocke ouer vvhich the holy Ghoſt had made them Biſhops: for of <hi>your owne ſelues ſhall men ariſe ſpeaking Peruerſe</hi> things: ſomtime the deuill may bring an Elder to that vvickedneſſe, and then ye ſee the other Elders are the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:4072:9"/>Biſhops that are to looke to it, and reforme it,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.31.</note> that office is not giuen to one in a dioceſſe. For as <hi>the Spirits of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets are ſubiect to the Prophets.</hi> So the Spirits of the Elders muſt in ſuch caſes be ſubiect to the Elders. VVheras if a Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>op fall into ſuch faults like the <hi>Appealer,</hi> he vvill be ſubiect to none: vvho dare aſke him? you vvill ſay the Archbiſhop: but if the Archbiſhop be corrupt and mightie in court, vvho dare once taxe him? The Pope. Adde he can not erre, or all is nothing. Such an endles labarinth, follovves this humaine inuention of dioceſſan, and prouinciall Biſhops: vvhich hath and doth make vvickednes abound, becauſe it hath not ſo good meanes to ſtay and repreſſe it, as the Elderſhip hath:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.28.</note> vvhich v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as ordained for that end, not by man but by God himſelfe. God hath ſet ſome in the church firſt Apoſtles, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condarily Prophets, thirdly Teachers then miracles, the gifts of healing, helpers, Gouernors, &amp;c. theſe laſt are tvvo diſtinct offices as Ar. Montan. Beza, and others reade them,<note n="*" place="margin">Beza. Annot. in hoc lec.</note> vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the helpers to be deacons, that helped the poore &amp; ſick And Gouernours to declare the order of the preſbyters, vvho vvere keepers of the diſcipline of the church, as vvee ſaid elſvvhere. To vvhom then belongeth the Gouernment, but to thoſe that God hath ſet in the church? Novv vvee can reade of no others that he ſet to gouerne, beſides the Apoſtles and Euangeliſt, but preſbyters. Hath God then ſet them for Gouernours in the church, &amp; vvill men preſume to ſupplant them, and ſet others? Dare men ſay that the gouernment, by dioceſſan Biſhops, ordained by men is better then this of Elders, ordained by God? To vvhome indeede God muſt needes giue a better bleſſing, as beeing his ovvne ordinance, he hath ſet them in the church. Neither doth that proue the contrarie, becauſe in Amſterdam, and ſom other cities of Holland, there are many Religions: for neither Biſhops, if they had ſuch, nor Elders can hinder it, if the pollicie ſuffer
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4072:10"/>them. But looke into the reformed churches there, in France, and elſvvhere, and you ſhall finde them better gouerned: and much better vvould be, if ſom burgers to enritch themſelues, and get places of authority, or a league, &amp; trade vvith Spaine, did not vvaxe negligent in religion, and for ſuch ends turne Arminians and nevvters. If an Apoſtle vvere novv liuing, and ſhould vvrite an Epiſtle to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Moulin paſtor and Elder in Sedan: <hi>Against an Elder receiue not an accuſation vnder two or there vvitneſſes,</hi> that vvould not argue, that he vvere ouer other Paſtors and Elders in the prouince; nor as a Lord in his ovvne congregation: but rather vvhat vvere his duty, yea the duty of all Elders aſſembled in ſuch a caſe.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle recounting all the officers, and Gouernours of the church,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.</note> ſaith, He gaue ſome Apoſtles: and ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: and ſome Paſtors, and Teachers: vvhere he neither na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes Biſhops nor Elders, much leſſe both, as tvvo diſtinct cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, becauſe the Paſtor by his place vvas a Preſbiter, and ſo a Biſhop properlie, &amp; the deacons had the care of the Almes. In ſuch a church, as that of Epheſus or Philippi, there vvere diuers, vvho vvere teachers and helpers, but one vvho vvas ſomevvhat more properlie the Paſtor, and ſo the biſhop of that flock: therefore though the charge go to all the Elders, <hi>Take beede to your ſelues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 2.</note> 
               <hi>and to all the flocke, &amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> yet this is ſomvvhat more eſpeciallie applied to him that is paſtor, and ſo the firſt Elder or biſhop. <hi>Vnto the Angel of the church of Epheſus</hi> vvrite, that is to the paſtor. Euen as in the church of Paris at this day, vvhich is one congregation, of about ſix thouſand communicants, there are three preachers, vvho are all Elders to feede the flock, yet one of them is reckoned the paſtor, &amp; the other tvvo helpers: the like in Diepe, and diuers other cities, vvhere they liue amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g perſecuting Papiſts, as the old Chriſtians did among the heathen: hauing but one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation or flock in a citie. In ſome leſſer cities, or vvhere
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4072:10"/>there are fevver proteſtants, there is only a paſtor vvith lay Elders. And thus out of all doubt,<note place="margin">Act. 14. Tit. 1.5.</note> it vvas in the primatiue church, till after the death of the Apoſtles, vvho ordained Elders in euerie church, and citie, vvhere one vvas the paſtor, yet in matter of gouernment, all the Elders of a church ruled together, by commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſent: euen in Ieruſalem things were not done vvithout the Elders, but the decrees vvent out in all their names. VVhen Paul vvent laſt to Ieruſalem, there vvere diuers vvith him: But, ſaith Luke,<note place="margin">Act. 21.18.</note> Paul <hi>vvent in vvith vs to Iames, &amp; all the Elders vvere preſent.</hi> The Apoſtle would doe nothing vvithout them. Therefore Paul ſaith,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.17.</note> 
               <hi>Let the Elders that rule vvell be counted vvorthy of double honour, eſpectiallie they vvho labour in the vvord &amp; doctrine.</hi> VVhence alſo ſom collect, that there vvere ſom Elders, that vvere not miniſters, but lay-men of the more vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, &amp; beſt gouerned ſort. Hovvſoeuer, ye ſee they had all ſhare in the gouernment vvere it vvith Timothie, Titus, or vvhoſoeuer. For theſe vvere not greater then the Apoſtles, vvhich vvas the higheſt calling in the church: yet euen vvith them in Ieruſalem, there vvere Elders, as it vvere in ioynt commiſſion for matter of gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: they themſelues tooke on them this office, &amp; diſdained not to be reckoned vvith other preſbiters. Peter ſaith,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.1.</note> The<note n="*" place="margin">or Elders. 2. Ioh.</note> preſbiters vvhich are among you, I exhort, vvho am alſo <hi>Sumpreſbuteros</hi> a fellovv preſbiter: and Iohn, that might haue ſaid, The Apoſtle, chooſeth rather to ſay, <hi>The Elder to the elect ladie, The</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">or Elder.</note> 
               <hi>Preſbiter to the vvelbeloued Gaius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>None of the Apoſtles are in the nevv Teſtament called biſhops, but preſbiters, becauſe a preſbiter vvas a biſhop, &amp; then a name of no leſſe honour, but rather of greater, beeing. Indeed one and the ſame paſtorall office in euerie congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it vvas the higheſt in the church next the Apoſtles, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſts, and paſtors, the Elders beeing the officers, vvhich God had appointed to gouern his church to the vvorlds end.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4072:11"/>The holy Ghoſt ſaith not Biſhops, leaſt aftervvard it ſhould haue bene take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for dioceſſan Biſhops but Elders. Neither doth Iohn ſet the Pope, or any Biſhop, but Chriſt among them, as their only head, for chap. 5. <hi>Christ ſtandeth in the midſt of the throne, and in the midst of the Elders,</hi> to ſhevv they truly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to his gouernment, as dioceſſan Biſhops, ſo that of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt It was ſtoutly defended in the councell of Trent,<note place="margin">Hiſtor. of the concell of Trent. pag. 599. &amp; 613. Rom. 13.1.</note> that they held, of the Pope &amp; not immediately of God True not ſo rightly as the Elders doe: nor yet in a manner ſo litle di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing as the firſt dioceſſan Biſhops did, as vve ſhall further ſee in the ſequel: therfore they are not ſo truly of Gods King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but rather of a contrarie, For indeede <hi>There is no power but of God: The powers that be are ordained of God.</hi> VVhence it follovves, that all povvers, much more thoſe that gouerne the church, muſt be ordained of God, or elſe they be not lavvfull. Novv this can not be ſaid of the Pope and Cardinals nor of Dioceſſan, Biſhops: for theſe vvere not ordained of God, but of men. Ergo &amp;c. They are indeede againſt Elders vvhich are the povvers ordained of God. <hi>VVhoſoeuer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reſisteth theſe powers, reſisteth the ordinance of God.</hi> One of the Elders ſpeakes to Iohn concerning the Martirs,<note place="margin">Reuel. 7.</note> that ſuffered in the ten perſecutions, ſignified by thoſe troubles that follovved the opening of the ſeauen ſeales, then paſt &amp; gone. And though vvhilſt the vvoman, the true Church fled, and remained in the vvildernes from Antichriſtian titannie and ſuperſtition, their gouernment muſt needes be hid, and perſecured vvith her: yet vvhen the Goſpell is reſtored, the Temple of God opened, &amp; diuers <hi>kingdoms of this vvorld, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the kingdoms of our Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 11.</note> 
               <hi>and of his Christ,</hi> the Elders vvorſhip &amp; giue thanks: as alſo vvhen Babilon is deſtroied: &amp; herevpon it is ſaid: <hi>The Lord God omnipotent reighneth:</hi> that is in his vvord and ordinances.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hap. 194.5.6.</note> Elders are then reſtored, vvhereas before ſhe &amp; her traditions, &amp; hierarchie gouerned
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4072:11"/>churches. For in that they are euer thus about the throne, on Seates, both before &amp; after Babilon is deſtroied, this ſheweth that they are the only ſpirituall Rulers, ordained by God; to gouerne his church vnder Chriſt, to the vvorlds end, and by him ſet about his throne, as thoſe vvhich by his ordinance haue had the <hi>Eccleſiasticall</hi> gouernment, ought ſtill to haue it by the furtherance of Chriſtian kings, and princes, that are nurſing fathers, and in Gods good time ſhall haue it againe. Chriſt vviloe in the midſt of the Elders. Both that of the Biſhop of Rome, and of all other dioceſſian, and prouinciall Biſhops, ſhall be ouerthrovven:<note place="margin">Iſa 9.7. Heb. 2.8.</note> and then of <hi>the increaſe of his gouernment, and peace there ſhall be no ende.</hi> but he vvill put all things in ſubiection <hi>vnder his feete.</hi> VVhich all as vvell high as lovv, ſhould endeauour to knovv, that knovving it, vvhen in praier they ſay, thy kingdome come, in heart they may both pray, that God vvould ſent it, and vſe the beſt meanes they can to effect it.</p>
            <p>By all vvhich is manifeſt, that the Preſbiters, vvere the Biſhops and Gouernours of the church, in the time of the Apoſtles, &amp; a vvhile after: and that the preeminence, vvhich after ſome one in a prouince obtained, vvas by conſent and cuſtome, &amp; not by authoritie of Scripture. VVhich is ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly acknovvledged by S. Auſtin.<note place="margin">Auguſt, in Epiſt. 19. ad Hibron. quae iam Eccleſiae vſus obti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuit. Ambroſ. comment. in cap. 4. ad Epheſ. Bellar. de clericis l. 4. cap. 4.</note> 
               <hi>For although according to the termes of honour, vvhich now the vſe of the church hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, a Biſhop vvhich is greater then the Preſbiterie, neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, Austin is in many things leſſe then</hi> Hierom, Note thoſe vvords, vvhich now the cuſtom of the church hath obtained, he ſaith not vvhich is giuen in the nevv Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Ambroſe ſaith, <hi>that of old the antienter Preſbiters, vvere called biſhops, that the eldeſt dying, the next might ſucceede him: but becauſe the following preſbiters, began to be found vnworthy to hold the primacie, the reaſon vvas changed vviſdome foreſeeing that not order but merrit ſhould make a biſhop, he vvas ordained by the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4072:12"/>choice of manie preiſts.</hi> VVhence vvee ſee, that the litle pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie, &amp; authoritie the biſhop had in his time gained, vvas not obtained all at a time, but by degrees: vvherin things had bene ſtill altered.<note place="margin">Bellar. 'de clericis lib 4. cap. 14.</note> VVich Bellarmin vvould faine denie, but can not: ſtriuing to make nothing of theſe, &amp; al other proofes: vvithout daring to taſke theſe fathers of hereſie: vvhich yet he boldly faſtens on Caluin,<note place="margin">Caluin. l. 4 Inſtit. c. 4.</note> Kemnitius, and others for hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſame things, and producing theſe proofes. Caluin, ſaith he, ſpeakes thus, <hi>Such as to vvhome the duty of teaching vvas enioined, vvere named preſbiters, they out of their number in diuers cities, chooſe one to vvhom they ſpecially gaue the title of a biſhop, leaſt out of equalitie, as it is vvont to be, diſcords ſhould ariſe: yet vvas not the biſhop ſo the ſuperiour in dignitie, and honour, that he ſhould haue lordſhip ouer his collegues: but looke vvhat priueleidges a Conſull hath in the Senate, to make report of the buiſneſſes, that by aduiſing, warning, &amp; perſwading he may preceede others, gouern the vvhole action by his authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and put in execution that, vvhich is determined by common conſent: the ſame office had the biſhop in the companie of the preſbiters: and that this verie thing vvas brought in for the neceſsitie of the time by humaine conſent, the ancient fathers themſelues confeſſe it, ye haue heard their teſtimonie.</hi> Againſt this Bellarmin for lack of better proofes alleadgeth the Acts of the Councell of Trent,<note place="margin">Vbi ſupra.</note> vvherein the biſhops vvere Iudges in their ovvne cauſe, as they had euer beene ſince the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Nice.</p>
            <p>In Trent it vvas alleadged <hi>that the Augustin confeſsion put noe difference betweene a biſhop,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſtor. of the Counc. of Trent. pag. 606.</note> 
               <hi>and a preist, but by humaine conſtitution, and affirmed the ſuperioritie of biſhops vvas first by custome, and after by Eccleſiasticall constitution.</hi> VVhich thoſe Trent fathers vvould faine haue diſproued, but could not. For though in the age after the Apoſtles, cuſtome had brought in a kinde of dioceſſan biſhops to preſide in Synods,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4072:12"/>yet in other reſpects, they vvere reckoned among other preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biters,<note place="margin">Euſeb. Hiſt. Eccleſiaſt. lib. 5. c. 22.23.24.</note> till about the yeere 195. vvhen Victor preſbiter or biſhop of Rome, tooke on him to excommunicate the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Aſia, about the feaſt of Eaſter, and for it, as Euſebius ſhevveth, vvas reproued by ſundrie biſhops: among the reſt by Ireneus in an Epiſtle to Victor. <hi>The Preists,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>which before Soter preſided in that church, vvhich you novv gouerne, namely, Anicetus, Pius, Higinus, Teleſphorus, and Xistus, neither obſerued that day themſelues, nor ſuffered others to obſerue it, yet they kept peace with others that did:</hi> vvhere note he calleth them not biſhops but Preiſts,<note n="*" place="margin">or preſbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</note> notvvithſtanding the eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of that church, and the cuſtome of preſiding among other preſbiters, as a kinde of dioceſſan: becauſe a preſbiter vvas a biſhop. Againe, <hi>But the preist vvhich vvere before you ſent vnto them, &amp;c.</hi> So fared <hi>it betweene</hi> Policarpus, and Anicetus the prieſt, that is the biſhop of Rome. It is true that after this proud and raſh act of Victor, the biſhop of Rome grevv greater, &amp; the name of a biſhop came to be more reſtrained to thoſe that liued in greate cities, and preſided in Synods: as alſo by that act of Steuen biſhop of Rome, vvho attempted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o reſtore Baſilides &amp; Martialis tvvo biſhops of Spaine about the yeere 250. And as Monſieur du Pleſſes obſerueth<note n="*" place="margin">Myſter. of Iniquit.</note> in the councell held at Rome vnder Sylueſter an. 324. <hi>the Preiſts ſtood behind the place vvhere the biſhops ſate.</hi> And in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Nice, held the yere after,<note place="margin">Concil. Nicen. 1. can. 6.7.</note> the 6. canon is read in theſe words, <hi>let the ancient cuſtomes be obſerued, vvhich are in Egipt, Lybia, &amp; Pentapolis, ſo that the biſhop vvhich is in Alexandria haue authoritie ouer all theſe, becauſe ſuch alſo is the manner or custome of the biſhop of Rome.</hi> VVhich is but a vveake autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for prouincial biſhops, ſeeing the canon confeſſeth, that it had beene only a thing of cuſtom: vvheras if it had bene an Apoſtolick inſtitution, the concell vvould rather haue alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged that. Mounſieur du<note n="*" place="margin">Vbi ſupra.</note> Pleſſes proues that many of the Ancient call it a cuſtome.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:4072:13"/>
Other things aduanced this dignity, &amp; the vvrath of God for it.<note place="margin">Cyprian. l. de lapſis. Euſeb. lib. 8. cap. 1.</note> Cyprian yealdeth this reaſon of the perſecution of <hi>Decius, becauſe euerie man ſlept in the coueteous deſires of his owne heart.</hi> VVhich he ſhevveth in the clergie. Euſebius giues a like reaſon of the ſucceeding perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Diocleſian, <hi>There vvas,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>amongst vs nought els, but curſed ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, &amp; continuall iarres of prelates, falling out vvith Prelates, &amp; congregations vvith congregations: They alſo vvhich ſeemed to be pastors, casting of this law, and rule of pietie kindled con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions betweene themſelues, ſeeking only to increaſe debates, threats, iealouſies, heart burnings and reuenge, vvith an immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate deſire to command and ſway, as in a Tyrannie.</hi> It is eaſie to conceiue, that vvhen peace and plentie came in, all things vvould vvaxe vvorſe. Conſtantine to bring his people to Chriſtianitie,<note place="margin">Anno 330. Damaſus &amp; Anaſtaſ. in vita Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt.</note> as he pulled dovvne Idolatrie, ſo he applied the reuenues of their Temples, to the maintenance of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian churches: and beſides gaue them other great gifts: his greateſt Princes, beeing conuerted, did the like, as appeares in the life of Sylueſt, and by Cedranus his Hiſtorie. S. Hierom, complaineth of Preiſts that vvrunge <hi>rewards from ladies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cedrenus pag. 243. Hieron. ad Euſtich. Epiſt. 22. Ad Nepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, 2. In God. Theodoſ.</note> 
               <hi>and from others. Others there are, vvho ſpend theire vvhole times in learntng the names, houſes, and qualities of theſe ladies.</hi> Ovid in another place, There be Clerks, vvhich poſſeſſe more vnder poore Chriſt, then erſt they did vnder the rich diuell. This contagion ſpread ſo far, that the Imperours, Valentinian, Valens &amp; Gratian, made lavves againſt it, <hi>prohibiting Clergie men to ſet foote vvithin the doores of vvidowes, or Orphans to receiuee gifts by Testament, &amp;c.</hi> VVith plentie came in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption in life and religion. Baronius confeſſeth that men at that time hallovved heatheniſh rites &amp; ceremonies,<note place="margin">Baro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. To 1. art. 44. art. 88. &amp;c. To. 3. art. 324. art. 78. &amp; 79.</note> by brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them into chriſtian churches: That Conſtantine ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>That the biſhops of the Christian lavve, ſhould thence for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard haue the ſame priueleidges, vvhich the idolatrous preiſts
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4072:13"/>had enioied.</hi> That the <hi>Pagan preiſts had a chiefe among them, Rex Sacrificulus, and their ſoueraigne Pontife, arbitrator of all questions among them.</hi> And vvho, ſaith he, can thinke, <hi>that Constantine vvould long endure, that theſe ſhould exceed the Christians</hi> in pompe and glory? then he proues the Pope and Cardinals to haue the like glory in riding, clothing, ſalutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and crovvning. VVhich is to ſhevv the Pope in habit of a pagan. Thus vvhile dioceſſan Biſhops vvere ordained, to vvithſtand diniſions, on the contrarie they vvere increaſed therby, as appeares by the reaſons Cyprian, &amp; Euſebius giue of the perſecutions, &amp; others about the feaſt of Eaſter, appeales, pride &amp; errours, in ſuch as was Paulus Semoſateneus, Arrius, Neſtorius, &amp; others, by whoſe great names,<note place="margin">Fuſeb. de vit. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. lib. 1. c. 37. &amp; 38.</note> groſſe errours were receiued, &amp; propagated. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantine, <hi>by reaſon of su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which he ſaw daily to ariſe betwene biſhops, aſſembled Synods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Novv to ſee more exactly hovv from ſo ſmall beginnings biſhops came to the greate power, they haue,<note place="margin">Hiſt. of the coure. of Trent pag. 226.</note> vvee may ſinde it proued in the hiſtorie of the councell of Trent: That at firſt the churches were gouerned by the common councell of the preſbitery, and how after to withſtand diuiſions, the monarchicall gouernment was inſtituted giuing ſuperintendency to the biſhop. The neighbour biſhops, whoſe churches becauſe they were vnder one prouince had commerce, did gouerne themſelues alſo by Synods: and to make the gouernment more eaſy, attributing much to the Biſhop of the principall citie, they made him as it were head of that body: and ſo the Biſhop of the citie, where the Ruler did reſide, gained a certaine ſuperiority by cuſtome. Theſe prefectures were the Imperiall citie of Rome: the prefecture of Alexandria, which gouerned Egypt, Libia, and Pentapolis: of Antioch for Syria, and other Prouinces of the Eaſt. This gouernment, brought in &amp; ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ued by cuſtom only, was eſtabliſhed by the firſt councell of Nice. The Pope had no other ground of his greatnes, ſaue this, and the tranſlation of the ſeate of the Empire from Rome to Conſtantinople, till about the yeere 607. vvhen he obtained of Phocas, that murdered his maſter, to be called vniuerſall Biſhop, vvhich title, vvas a litle before proued to be Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, by his Predeceſſor Gregorie, 1. The inundation of the Gothes, and Vandals had eclipſed his glorie,<note place="margin">Guiciard.</note> and ſo did
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:4072:14"/>the Fxarchs of Rauenna, till the Lombards, hauing gotten that Exarchat, &amp; long oppreſſed all Italie, Pipin chaſed them avvay, and gaue this part to the Biſhop, &amp; church of Rome: vvhich vvas confirmed by his Sonne Charles, that vtterlie rooted the Lombards out, and vvas by the Pope crovvned Emperour: yet the Popes vvere ſubiect to him, till his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie grovving vveake, ſeuen Electors vvere ordained, and the Imperiall povver, being tranſlated to the Germans, and noe longer hereditarie, vvas much diminiſhed, and that of the Popes thereby increaſed, eſpetially, after they obtained of the Emperour Henry the ſecond, that the Cardinals only ſhould chooſe the Pope, and then the Cardinals alſo vvaxed great.</p>
            <p>If this ſhevv not hovv biſhops, but rather hovv the Pope grevv greate, it is ſupplied by another diſcourſe in the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the councell of Trent, vvhere it being conſidered, in vvhat caſes Chriſt ſaith,<note place="margin">Mat. 18.17.</note> Tell the church, and vvhat povver is giuen to a congregation, in that place to the Corinthians, vve may ſee hovv things vvere carried after dioceſſan Biſhops vvere thus ordained.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.4.</note> The iudgment of the church (as is neceſſary in euery multitude) was fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Hiſtor. of the concell of Trent pag. 330. to pag. 335.</note> hat it ſhould be conducted by one, who ſhould preſide, and guide the action. This care, due to the moſt principall, and worthy perſon was alwaies committed to the Biſhop. And where the churches were many, the propoſitions, and deliberations were made by the Biſhop firſt in the colledge of Preiſts, and Deacons, which they called the Preſbiterie, and there were ripened, to receiue afterward the laſt reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in the generall congregation of the church. This forme was ſtill on foote in the yeere 250. &amp; is plainly ſeene by the Epiſtles of Cyprian, who in matter concerning thoſe who did eate of meates offered to Idols, and ſubſeribe to the Religion of the Gentiles, writeth to the Preſbiterie, that he doth not thinke to do any thing without their counſells, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the people: and writeth to the people, that, at his retourne, he will examine the cauſes, and merits thereof, in their preſence, and vnder their iudgment and he wrote to thoſe Preiſts, who of their owne braine had reconciled ſome, that they ſhould giue an account to the people. I muſt here referre you to the Hiſtorie it ſelfe, vvhich ſheweth hovv this gouernment had bene defended againſt the Canoniſts, &amp; only recite ſom things to ſhevv hovv it decaied, &amp; hovv in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:4072:14"/>the ruine thereof, that of the Biſhops increaſed; vvherein if I ſtriue to much too abridge things, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſult the with place it ſelfe for better ſatisfaction. The goodneſſe and Charitie of the Biſhops,<note place="margin">I dem vbi ſupra.</note> made their opinion for the moſt part to be followed, &amp; by title and litle, was cauſe that the churches, charity waxing cold, not regarding the charge laide vpon them by Chriſt, did leaue the care to the Biſhop: and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a wittie paſſion, which doth inſinuate it ſelfe in ſhew of vertue, cauſed it to be readily embraced. But the principall cauſe of the change was the ceaſing of the perſecutions. For then the Biſhops did erect as it were a tribunall, which was much frequented: becauſe as temporall commodities, ſo ſuits did increaſe. The iudgment though diſtering from the former in forme, to determine all by the opinion of the church, was yet of the ſame ſinceritie. Which Conſtantine obſeruing, made a law, that there ſhould lie no appeale from the ſentences of Biſhops: and if in a cauſe depending before a ſecular tribunall, either of the parties ſhall demand Epiſcopall iudgment, the cauſe ſhalbe remitted to him. Here the tribunall of the Biſhop began to be a common pleading place. The Emperour Valence enlarging it in the yeere 365. gaue the Biſhops the care ouer all the prizes of vindible things. Which troubled Auſtin, and other good Biſhops. Afterwards ſome Biſhops beginning to abuſe the power giuen them by Conſtantine, that law was 70. yeeres after, reuoked by Arcadius, and an ordination made that they ſhould iudge cauſes of religion, and not ciuill, except both parties did conſent, and declared that they ſhould not be thought to haue a court. Which law beeing not much obſerued in Rome, in regard of the greate power of the Biſhop, Valentinian, being then in the citie, an. 452. did renew it, and made it to be put in execution. But a litle after part of the power taken away, was reſtored by the following Princes: So that Iuſtinian eſtabliſhed vnto them a court, and audience, the cauſes of Religion, Eccleſiaſticall faults of the clergie, &amp; diuers voluntarie ſuriſdictions ouer the laietie. By theſe degrees they got domination.</p>
            <p>The Empire being diuided, and kingdoms erected,<note place="margin">Idem pag. 332.</note> the Biſhops for the moſt part were made councellors of the Prince, which by mixture of ſpirituall and temporall charges, cauſed their iuriſdiction to increaſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly. Before 200. yeeres were paſt, they pretended abſolutely all iudicature, criminall, and ciuill, ouer the Clergie, and in ſome things ouer the laietie. After the yeere 1050. All the cauſes of the Clergie beeing appropriated to the Biſhops, and verie many of the laieſie, vnder the title of ſpiritualitie, and almoſt all the reſt vnder the name of a mixed iudicature, and placing themſelues aboue the ſecular Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, vpon pretence of iuſtice denied, they came to ſay that the Biſhop, had that power to iudge, not by graunt, or conniuence of Princes,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:4072:15"/>or by the will of the people, or by cuſtome, but that it was eſſentiall to the Epiſcopall dignitie, and giuen it by Chriſt. And though the lawes of the Emperours remaine in the Codes of Theodoſius and Iuſtinian, in the capitulars of Charles the greate, and Lewis the debonaire, and others of later Princes, which all ſhew, when, &amp; by whome this power was graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and all Hiſtories Eccleſiaſticall, and prophane agree in the ſame: yet ſo notorious a truth hath bene ouercome, by a contrary affirmation only, without any proofe.<note place="margin">Pag. 334.</note> In the councell of Trent a defect was conſidered, that the charitie of the ſuperiours was turned into domination, and that thence grew appeale vpon appeale. Iohannes Groperus, who aſſiſted there as a diuine, and a lawier, ſpake honourably of appeales, &amp; ſaid that while the heare of faith remained in the breaſts of Chriſtians, Appeales were not heard of. But charitie in the Iudges waxing cold, and place being giuen to paſſion, they entred into the church, for the ſame reaſons, which brought them into the ſecular courts, that is, for the eaſe of the oppreſſed. And as the firſt iudicatures belonged not to the biſhop only, but to him with the councell of his Preiſts, ſo the Appeale was not diuolued to one man, but vnto another congregation. But the Biſhops taking away the Synods, did inſtitute courts and officers, like the ſeculars. Neither did the miſchiefe ſtop there, but paſſed to greater abuſes then in the ſecular court. Which he ſhewes in that Appeale, was made from Appeale, till it came to the Pope, and ſomtime by a leap to him without more a doe. Iohn Baptiſta, Caſtellus vvas made to ſalue vp theſe ſoares, by a <hi>cunning oration,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 335. and 336.</note> in the next congregation. And ſo, to reſtore Synodall iudicatures was reiected almoſt by all, becauſe it did diminiſh the Epiſcopall, &amp; was too popular. For proceeding againſt the perſons of the Biſhops, no man deſiring to facilitate the iudicature againſt himſelfe, the reſtoring of it to parochiall Synods, vnto which it did formerly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, was not ſpoken of Engliſh Biſhops in like wiſdome ſuppreſſe all bookes, &amp; Preachers that ſpeake of the right of Elders, or of ſuch Synods and the like things, that neither theu nor their owne vſurpations, may be knowne. By all vvhich vvee may ſee, that it is a vveake de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, for the authoritie of Biſhops, &amp; againſt the Elderſhip, to alleadge the grant of Emperours &amp; Kings, or as Bellarmin doth the Acts of any councell, much leſſe that of Trent. Gods ordinance &amp; vvord, ſhould euer be of more force, &amp; eſteeme vvith true Chriſtians, then any of this kinde vvhatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>By theſe affirmations of this impartiall Author, vvhome they can not call a Brovvniſt, or a Puritan, vvee may ſee, that they in the church of England, vvho vnderſtand this clauſe,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4072:15"/>
               <hi>Tell the church,</hi> as if it vvere meant, tell the Biſhops, or their Officials, doe not only vvilfully vnderſtand it, as Chriſt neuer meant it, &amp; of ſuch as he neuer ordained, but euen contrarie to the interpretation, vnderſtanding, and practiſe of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue church till the time of Cyprian, that is for 250. yeers after Chriſt. VVhich ſhevves the Gouernment of Dioceſſan Biſhops, &amp; their Officials, Chancellors, Courts, and procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings to be popiſh, nouell, &amp; intollerable: ſuch as make the ordinance of God of none effect, &amp; take things vpon them, vvhich belong not to them. If a man dvvelling in the Iſle of Iereſey, in the Iſle of vvight, or in Surrey, find himſelfe much vvronged &amp; moleſted by a neighbour, vvould <hi>Tell the church:</hi> ſhould he run to the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, or to his Chancelour at VVincheſter, and not rather to the flock, and the Elders thereof, vvhereof he and the offendour are members? vvhich flock ſhould, haue the povver the church of Corinth had.</p>
            <p>It is remarkeable, that vvhen Chriſt vvould reproue the ſeuen churches for certaine corruptions crept into them, he doth not ſay vvrite, and ſend it to the chiefe officers of the church, to the Archbiſhops, biſhops, or their officials, Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celours, &amp;c. For there vvere no ſuch officers then, but vvrite, and ſend it vnto the ſeuen churches,<note place="margin">Reu. 1.11.</note> that is to the vvhole flock in Epheſus, ſo to that in Smyrna, and ſo in all the reſt. So it is ſtill added, <hi>Let him that hath an eare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">chap. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>heare vvhat the Spirit ſaith to the churches.</hi> Euerie man that vvas a member of the church muſt heare it, and take care to redreſſe it. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he bids him vvrite to the Angel, that is to the Paſtor of the church of Epheſus, and ſo of the reſt, becauſe the Paſtor as the principall man, and a Preſident in the congregation, ſhould propound, and make it knovvne to the reſt, he being one vvhome it did a litle more concerne then the reſt, as he vvas Shepheard of the flock, &amp; ſo one that ſhould looke to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:4072:16"/>ſuch faults: yet all the Elders of euerie church, vvere alſo to looke to it, as thoſe that had ſhare in the gouernment, and things vvere determined by voices of all men, members of the church. The Epiſtles vvere vvritten to them all, as appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ares alſo by that to the church of Smyrna: <hi>the deuill ſhall caſt ſome of you into priſon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 10.22 23.</note> 
               <hi>I vvill giue vnto euerie one of you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his vvorks: And vnto you I ſay, the rest of them of Thiatira, as many as haue not this learning, &amp;c.</hi> VVhen he ſaith, of ſome churches, that they had kept his name, and not denied the faith, &amp;c. and of others that they had left <hi>their firſt loue,</hi> or had them vvhich <hi>held the doctrine of the Nicolaitans, of Balaam,</hi> or the vvoman lezabel: It is ſenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les to thinke, that only the Angel of each church is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended or taxed. The reproofes, and incitements to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance are not to him alone, but to the church. Paul ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to the church of the Coloſſians,<note place="margin">Col. 4.17.</note> ſaith, <hi>Say to Archippus, Take heede to the ministrie, that thou hast receiued in the Lord, that thou fulfill it.</hi> He vvrit his Epiſtles, vvherein their are directions for gouernment, to the churches. He vvilleth the church at Rome,<note place="margin">Rom. 16.17.</note> 
               <hi>to marke them vvhich cauſe diuiſions, and offences, contrarie to the doctrine they</hi> had learned, and to auoyde them. In that greate buſines, Act. 15. the brethren vvere at the diſcuſſing of it, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees vvent out in all their names. <hi>It ſeemed good to the Apostles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act 15.22.23.</note> 
               <hi>and Elders, vvith the</hi> vvhole church. Letters vvere vvritten <hi>after this manner,</hi> The Apoſtles, and Elders, and <hi>brethren, vnto the brethren, &amp;c.</hi> And in that it is ſaid,<note place="margin">Verſ. 12.</note> 
               <hi>All the multitude kept ſilence, and heard Barnabas, &amp;c.</hi> All this ſhevves they had libertie to ſpeake in due time, if they had ſeene cauſe.<note place="margin">Act. 6.5.</note> 
               <hi>The ſaying pleaſed the multitude.</hi> This ſhevves their conſent, and that they had voices. For as Paul informed by the houſe of Cloe, that there
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4072:16"/>vvere <hi>diuiſions</hi> among them,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.</note> conuinced them as an Apoſtle vvith vvords, vvhich are the vvord of God: ſo vvhen by them, or by ſuch others, he vvas informed of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtious Corinthian, he conuinced them, yet he referred the cenſure to the church,<note place="margin">Chap. 5.4.</note> and vvould not doe the thing himſelfe, though as an Apoſtle he vvas a generall officer in all churches. He vviſheth them to excommunicate him: and after vvhen he had repented<note n="*" place="margin">2. Cor. 2.7.</note> to <hi>forgiue</hi> him. It is true that the <hi>Keies</hi> of binding, and looſing in this kinde, vvere principallie giuen to the Paſtors: but ye ſee they did not excommunicate, and reſtore vvithout the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the church.</p>
            <p>And yet it is not meant hereby, that this parochiall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment ſhould be ouerloaden vvith buſineſſes: much leſſe vvith friuilous contentions. For ſome things may be ended by the arbitration of tvvo or three neighbours, and many cauſes are fitter for the common lavves, and thoſe courts vvhere the Kings Chancellour, and other Iudges ſit, but only that ſuch matters ſhould be in the churches povver, as are fit, that the church ſhould take care of them, and iudge them. So that this doth not ouerthrovv the authoritie of Chriſtian Magiſtrates, and their courts. Neither can this be a cauſe of confuſion, making that vvhich is all mens buſines, to be no mans: ſo that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon carelesnes ſhould ariſe, or pride, and contention. For vvee ſee, that after this manner, many things haue beene vvell diſcuſſed, and determined in the high court of Parliament, vvhere all things paſſe by voices: as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vviſe in ciuill corporations, and common counſailes: In vvhich, things are beſt, and moſt vncorruptlie car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, vvhen men may ſpeake their mindes freelie, and are not oueravved by ſuch greate ones, as are the Biſhops,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:4072:17"/>that haue povver to ſit on their ſkirts that diſpleaſe them. For in this caſe men ſhould thinke of that,<note place="margin">Mat. 23.8.</note> 
               <hi>One is your maſter euen Christ, &amp; ye are brethren. Doe ye not know that the ſaints ſhall iudge the vvorld?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.6. chap. 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>He that is ſpirituall diſcerneth all things.</hi> And thinke vvee then, that they may not as vvell be fit Iudges of manners novv, as they vvere in the Apoſtles time, and the age next after them? If it vvere once in vſe, men vvould ſoone be vvell enabled to the vvorke.</p>
            <p>Beſides the proofes out of Cyprian aboue mentioned,<note place="margin">Tertull. Apol. c. 39. lib. 3. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra a piſt. Parment.</note> Tertullian makes the officers to be only <hi>Preſidents in the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie:</hi> Hierom ad Demet. affirmes, that <hi>the church it ſelfe hath right in excommunication, as the Elders haue in other church cenſures.</hi> Auguſtin thinks that <hi>it helpes much to the ſhaming of the partie, that he be excommunicate by the vvhole church.</hi> Zvvinglius, Artie. 8. explanat. ſpeaking of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention vvhich hath bene, vvhat a church is, acknovvledges no other churches, but 1. <hi>the companie of ſure, and firme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers diſperſed through the vvhole vvorld,</hi> called the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick church. And 2, ſeuerall congregations vvhich <hi>conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently meete together in ſome one place, &amp;c.</hi> of theſe he affirmes Chriſt to ſpeake Mat. 18. <hi>Tell the church.</hi> Peter Martyr in his common places, Pant. 4. chap. 5. Sect. 9 making the church a Monarchie in reſpect of Chriſt, an Ariſtocracie in reſpect of the Elders, addeth alſo, that <hi>becauſe in the church, there are matters of greate vveight, and importance, referred vnto the people, as excommunication, abſolution, chooſing Miniſters, and the like, it hath alſo a conſideration of popular gouernment:</hi> and vpon 1. Cor. 5.4. <hi>The Apostle, as greate as he vvas vvould not excommunicate alone, but did take counſaile vvith the church that the thing might be done by common authority. VVhich not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvithſtanding both Romiſh, &amp; Engliſh biſhops dare doe. The Apostle indeede goes before the reſt, vvhich is the duty of the ancients of the church, that the more ignorant multitude, by their
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:4072:17"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uffrages goeing before, may be directed, iudging.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib 1. de regno Chriſti cap. 9.</note> Bucer affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, that Paul <hi>accuſes the Corinthians, for that the vvhole church had not excommunicated the inceſtious perſons.</hi> Baſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius, Loc. 4. queſt. 85. of his Catechiſme, ſpeaking of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betvveene the tvvo keies, that of preaching, and the other of diſcipline, placeth it in this, that the former, vvhich is <hi>of the preaching of the Goſpel, is committed to the ministers, the other, becauſe it pertaines to the diſcipline of excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is permitted to the vvhole church.</hi> I omit that vvhich M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Foxe, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cartvvright, and other Engliſh men had ſaid to this purpoſe, becauſe it vvould be too long for this place.</p>
            <p>It vvilbe obiected, that many learned Engliſh men, hold better vvith the Epiſcopall gouernment. I anſvvere, the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of conformitie, impoſed on them furniſheth them vvith arguments to that purpoſe. They knovv the Biſhops can not looke to all things neceſſarie in euerie pariſh. But, ſay they, there are church vvardens, &amp; ſide men: They might adde vvhoſe office ſerues to litle, but to looke to the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of their traditions, and ceremonies, and therefore not for the kingdome of God, but for the dominion of Biſhops: they are but a mockerie of the Elderſhip. They knovv, that if the pariſh be full of prophane Svvearers, drunkards, forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cators, extortioners, defrauders, and the like, all theſe in their turnes may come to be churchvvardens. If they be but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to ceremonies, and do but ſpeake vvell of the booke of common praier, though they haue no true loue to preaching, and hearing of the vvord, vvhereby, knovvledge, faith, and other graces are vvrought in the ſoule, but ſcorne, and mocke them that haue: they yet thinke themſelues the better ſubiects, the better Chriſtians, yea fitter to be church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvardens then profeſſors: and the Biſhops, finding them to be a bridle to ſuch religious ſpirits, are vvell contented, kow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng ſuch ignorant conformiſts, are fitteſt for their turnes.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:4072:18"/>(If the perſon or curate be alſo a Droane, a non reſident, or a good fellovv, there is a flock ſtrangely gouerned) ſuch are not apt for the kingdome of God, the blind can not leade the blind, the drunkard reforme drunkards. Theſe vvill neuer informe the Biſhop of corruption in manners, much leſſe in doctrine, ſuch as ſhames the Chriſtian profeſſion. And if they did, he is but one, he can not looke to things in euerie flock to knovv euerie ſheepe, as Elders may in one congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. If men had not the ceremonies, and ſeruice, to ſerue them for an intire religion, or a cloake of one, they could not for ſhame, but make ſome profeſſion of loue to the vvord, &amp; good conuerſation. If there vvere but three, or fovver reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious men in a pariſh to be the officers, their example might moue the reſt, ſuch could not be ſcorned as they are. In the reformed churches men are aſhamed to ſcorne profeſſors, if they did, they ſhould be reckoned prophane, and ſoone be queſtioned; it vvould not ſerue them to ſay they loue the common praiers, they ſhould ſoone be taught to knovv, that <hi>He that turnes away his eare from hearing of the law his praier ſhalbe abhominable.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 28.9.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. By all this vvee may ſee, that thoſe abuſe the vvorld, vvho for the authoritie of Engliſh Biſhops, and the Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie there, alledge the ſucceſſion of lames at Ieruſalem, of Peter at Antioch, of Marke at Alexandria, of Timothie at Epheſus, &amp; Titus in Creete. For vvee ſee there vvere no ſuch Lord Biſhops, Courts, Chancellours, and proceedings as are novv. The Apoſtles oft ſtaied in theſe places, and looked to things as generall officers in all churches: but vſed no ſuch Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſc pall authoritie as ours doe, vvho come not in by the word, that is by Chriſt the <hi>Doore,</hi> but clim vp another vvay, by the traditions,<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.</note> and corruptions of men, like theeues that come to ſteale to fle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce and not to feede the flock. Ciuill go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernments may vpon good reaſons be altered, &amp; a nevv ſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:4072:18"/>of officers ordained. But Chriſt that changeth not, ſet officers in his kingdome to gouerne, and therein the perfit forme of his kingdome: the church is a kingdome, vvhich can not be ſhaken. Timothie vvas an Euangeliſt,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.28.</note> but hath no ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours in that office, noe more can the Apoſtles in theirs: they left to ſeuerall congregations, the choice of Preſbyters, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring of offendours, and debating of matters as is alreadie proued. Other ſucceſſours they haue not,<note n="*" place="margin">To go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne. Bellarm. de clericis l. 1. c. 14.</note> as Papiſts are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vered for Peters being at Rome To as good purpoſe Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, and others thinke to make men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lee from this opinion, as from a monſter, by ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ying it vvas the heriſie of Aerius. <hi>Medinae</hi> cited by Bellarmin affirmes, that S. Hierom <hi>vvas herein vvholly of the opinion of the Aerians, and that not only S. Hierom vvas in that hereſie, but alſo Ambroſe, Auguſtine, Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius, Primaſius, Chryſostom, Theodoret, Oecumemus and Theophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius, And ſo</hi> ſaith Medina, <hi>the opinion of thoſe fathers, otherwiſe verie holy, and expert in the holy Scriptures, vvas by the church firſt condemned in Aerius, then in the</hi> VValdenſes, <hi>and lastly</hi> in Iohn vvicklife. And againe <hi>Of old therefore this opinion vvas diſſembled, and tollerated in</hi> Hierom, <hi>and thoſe</hi> Greeke Fathers <hi>for their honour, and reuerence: contrariwiſe in the hereticks, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are alſo eſtranged from the church in other things, it hath bene alwaies condemned as hereticall.</hi> Bellarmine ſticks not to ſay, <hi>Medina</hi> wanted vvit,<note place="margin">Hiſt. of the counc. of Trent. pag. 591.</note> in being thus plaine knowing it had bene maintained in Trent, &amp; that men vvould be ready to affirme, if this be not hereſie in Hierom, and thoſe other fathers, neither can it be iuſtlie called ſo in Aerius, vvho liued in the ſame times. VVhich Kemnitius ſpares not to manifeſt,<note place="margin">Examen. conc. Trid.</note> ſhevving that it vvas an ordinarie trick in thoſe times, vvhen they could not anſvvere a mans arguments, to diſgrace him vvith the name of hereſie. Bellarmin ſaith,<note place="margin">Vbi ſupra.</note> 
               <hi>That all the fathers conſtantly taught that biſhops ſuceede the Apoſtles, &amp; Preſbyters</hi> the 70. diſciples. I anſvvere 1. vvee haue proued the contrarie out of Hierom, &amp; others, 2. That Preſbyters who are Biſhops
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:4072:19"/>may ſucceede the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Mat. 28.20</note> as they vvere Paſtors, and Elders of any church, as Peter and Iohn call themſelues, and as Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothie, and Titus vvere, and ſo that may be vnderſtood, I am vvith you alvvaies to the end of the vvorld, in their ſucceſſours as they vvere, Paſtors, Teachers, and Elders, but not as they vvere Apoſtles, and ſo ouer Titus, Timothie, and all Elders. For to be an Apoſtle is to be ſent immediatly from God, to haue an Embaſſage from him, and as <hi>a maister builder to lay the foundation for others to build vpon:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.10. Tit. 1.5.</note> &amp; to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, and appoint things, as Paul did. This did the Apoſtles in their Goſpels, Epiſtles, and Acts. But this can not Biſhops do: for they are not ſo ſent immediatly from God, hauing an immediate embaſſage: they haue theirs from the Apoſtles, and Prophets, and ſo mediately. Neither are they maiſter builders, to lay a fondation for others to build vpon, though they oft aſſume it in impoſing their traditions, and rites for lavves: for <hi>other foundation can no man lay, then that is laide, vvhich is Ieſus Christ.</hi> Therfore the Apoſtles can noe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vviſe haue Succeſſours, then as they vvere Paſtors, and Elders, &amp; that muſt be in teaching the ſame, &amp;<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 1.8.</note> noe other doctrine, <hi>Medina</hi> alledged by Bellarmin,<note n="*" place="margin">Vbi ſupra</note> ſaith, <hi>The hereticks the vval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſes vſed the teſtimonie of Hierom, they therefore, and Hierom vvere of one opinion,</hi> that is, that the church ought to be gouerned by Preſbiters, and that the gouernment by dioceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan Biſhops is of humaine authoritie, and inuention: and conſequently <hi>the vviſdome of the fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.7.</note> vvhich is <hi>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mitie vvith God: for it is not ſubiect to the law of God, neither indeede can be.</hi> As vvee may ſee in thoſe greate defendors of the Hierarchie in the church of Rome, and in England, that vvill not be conuinced, in this point, by the Teſtament of Chriſt. So much are they blinded by the proffit, and honour, that follovves it, but crie out that this is nothing, but the madnes of the Brovvniſts, and ſome others that ſeeke innovation, &amp; change, that theſe are priuate ſpirits, and that they giue a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:4072:19"/>priuate interpretation of the ſcriptures, and Fathers, becauſe it agrees not vvith theirs, vvho are more in number, and greater in povver. VVhich yet is the <hi>priuate interpretation,</hi> becauſe not according to the expreſſe meaning of the holy Ghoſt. The conſent of many clocks, and vvatches in a citie, doth not proue them to goe true, vnles they accord vvith the Sunne: No more doth that of many Biſhops, and Councels, vnles they agree vvith the vvord. One Paphnutius hauing that on his ſide is not a priuate ſpirit, but ought to be prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before many of a contrarie concord, as the Councell of Nice ſhevved in him. Therefore, it is but a ſhift, and a moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerie to call this <hi>Tenet</hi> Brovvniſme, vvhen they knovv this of the Elderſhip is the gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the reformed churches in France, Germanie, &amp;c. and that to condemne this for an errour, is to condemne them all, yea the fathers before alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and the verie Apoſtles themſelues.</p>
            <p>It vvill be obiected, Dioceſſan Biſhops came in, ſoone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of the Apoſtles: and if the church gouerned by Elders be the true church, vvhere vvas the true church from the firſt comming in of dioceſſan Biſhops, till the Nicene Councell, vvhen they vvere firſt confirmed by a generall councell, and Imperiall authoritie, <hi>and the vvoman fled into the vvildernes,</hi> and vvas follovved by a flood of Gothes,<note place="margin">Reuel. 12.</note> and Vandals: I anſvvere, Biſhops vvere then dioceſſan, &amp; prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, rather <hi>nomine, quam re,</hi> in name then indeed, excerciſing title povver, and authoritie ouer them, as ye haue ſeene out of the teſtimonie of Cyprian, Hierom, and Chryſoſtom. <hi>VVhat doeth the biſhop, giuing of orders excepted, vvhich the Preſbyter may not doe?</hi> He vvas not then come to his power, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſtrength, but vvas then litle other then a Preſbyter in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atter of gouernment, had a Paſtorall charge ouer one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>regation, yea gouerned like them, and vvith them: the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yters had their voices in Councels, they neither vvere nor
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:4072:20"/>vvould be ſo ſoone thruſt out. So that for a time, they had ſtill the eſſentiall parts of a true church: at leaſt till ſuch ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and blemiſhes grevv greater, &amp; the Hierarchie excerciſed more authoritie ouer the Preſbiters, and became the mint, defence, &amp; authority of humaine inuentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, errour &amp; ſuperfli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; to be made a marke of a true church. Then the miſtery of iniquitie, that had long before vvrought, in that inuentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, began to ſhevv the fruits thereof: then that vvas true vvhich one ſaith of epiſcopacie, <hi>It vvas inuented against an euill, but the remedy proued worſe then the diſeaſe.</hi> For out of theſe ſmal beginnings, iſſued. 1. The inſupportable povver, &amp; impietie of the Pope, and church of Rome: vvhich haue brought ſo many, and ſo vnſpeakeable euills on the church. For though perhaps thoſe ancients meant to doe noe hurt, but rather much good, in ordaining dioceſſan Biſhops, and giuing them but litle power: yet hereby the miſterie of iniquity wrough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for they thus preſuming to ſet one ouer others in a dioceſſe, this povver increaſed: &amp; vvith like reaſon, &amp; authoritie Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, and Patriarcks vvere ſet ouer Biſhops, &amp; in the end a Pope ouer all. For grant they may ordaine dioceſſan Biſhops, and that their ordinance is by a diuine inſtinct, and of good authoritie, and it vvill fellovv, that others after them, may as vvell ordaine the reſt: and that their ordinance alſo is by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine inſtinct, and of good authoritie: &amp; ſo indeed to ordaine Cardinals, and as manie vpſtart orders of Prieſts, and friers, as are among the Papiſts. I might add ſetting vp of Images to be vvorſhipped, and all other popiſh <hi>Tenets,</hi> and cuſtomes, vvhich haue bene authoriſed by councels, and kings, if that vvere ſufficient, as ſome thinke it is.</p>
            <p>Hence therefore as from a ſpring haue iſſued all the errours of the Romiſh church, eſtabliſhed by Biſhops in councels for ſound, and good doctrines, and all the vaſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and povver of Biſhops, and the multitude of thoſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:4072:20"/>traditions, and ceremonies, vvherevvith, they as Rulers, haue burdened the church, and by vvhich the vvord of God hath bene made of none effect: So that novv neither the Romiſh, nor Engliſh, Biſhops, vvill endure that the ſcriptures ſhould be alledged in theſe points of their Hierarchie, &amp; traditions: and many as vvell of the Princes, and Clergie, as of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, ſeeing the name, and office of a Biſhop in the Scriptures, are contented vvith the Biſhops, to take it for graunted, that it is meant of dioceſſan Biſhops, that the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the church, vvas in the nevv Teſtament giuen to them, &amp; not to Elders: or at leaſt as others inferre, As the church vvas enlarged, vnder the old title of biſhops a nevv order of gouernment might be ordained by counſailes of men, and authoritie of Emperours, and kings, for the better gouernment of the church. As if any thing could be better deuiſed, or bring forth better fruite, then the ordinance of God: vvho hath puniſhed, that preſumption vvith ſo ill fruites of it, to make vs ſee the contrarie: or as if the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God vvere inſufficient, and he had not as ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie prouided for his church in this point, as in others. He vvill teach vs at length to knovv the tree by the fruit: and that theſe great places in the Hierarchie, are but meere baites to corrupt men: and make them to pleaſe ſuch biſhops, and courtiers as can aduance them, ofters bribes, vvreſt the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures for the Hierarchie, Arminiaiſme, and ſuch popiſh points, traditions, and ceremonies, as make the vvord of God of none effect.</p>
            <p>Neither is it any reaſoning from the time of Auguſtin, and thoſe fathers, that ſavv Dioceſſan Biſhops, and ſaid not much againſt them, but rather ſeemed to thinke their vſe, tollerable, and proffitable, and them to be hereticks, that denied it, beeing eſtabliſhed by councels.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:4072:21"/>
1. Becauſe the povver of Biſhops, as vve proued in thoſe daies, vvas nothing like that they novv haue, but as one ſaith, as vnlike, as the povver of the Duke of Venice in the Senate, is to that vvhich ſome Monarch hath in his dominions, and ouer his ſubiects.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe Fathers had not ſeene ſuch fruits of it, in Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and Antichriſtian povver, as vve haue: and ſo vvhat it is to take ſuch a cuſtome, or an ordinance of a Concell, for a good vvarrant. So many traditions, and ſuperſtitious rites vvere not then inuented, much leſſe propoſed as lavves by the Epiſcopall povver.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That it is no reaſoning from the conſent, or continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the fathers, if the inſtitution be not vvarrantable by Gods vvord. Neither they nor a generall Councell, nor Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, &amp; kings, can make that to be <hi>ex iure diuine,</hi> vvhich is not ſo by Gods Teſtament. Men vvill not preſume to make other Ouerſeers to a mans Teſtament, then he hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to ſee it performed, much leſſe ought they to doe it to Gods, as they haue in ordaining dioceſſan Biſhops, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering them to obſcure, and annihilate thoſe places of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, vvherein God giues the Eccleſiaſticall gouernment to the Preſbyters, or ſacrilegiouſly to vſurpe, and applie them to any gouernment, ſo contrarie to the Elderſhip, as that of the Hierarchie is. Theſe paſſages of the nevv Teſtament are <hi>the letters Patents of the Preſbyterie:</hi> and yet dioceſſan Biſhops doe not only vſurpe them, as Papiſts doe ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for the Pope, and make them ſerue to authoriſe a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary gouernment, moſt pernicious to the ordinance of God, but quite exclude the Preſbyters, to vvhome they vvere granted, from the gouernment, and from that effectuall povver in Synods, vvhich is due to them. &amp; not to Biſhops: vvho could not vvell be oppoſed in the Nicene Councell, becauſe the hurt, and vvrong that Biſhops doe to Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:4072:21"/>kingdome could not be ſo manifeſt to Conſtantine, and his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onnes, nor ſo euident in the time of Cyprian, and Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſius, as it vvas ſince, or novv is. Euen as the Lion, or Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ard doth but litle harme, vvhile it is but a litle vvhelpe. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>deed they had not ſuch dominion ouer Preſbiters, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ch courts, Chancellours, Officials, Dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, povver in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ues of vvilles, and Teſtaments, much leſſe in forbidding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he defence of the truth againſt Pelagians: nor ſuch Rules, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ceremonies to ſuſpend, and ſilence about ſurpleſſes, cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, &amp;c. Neither can the church giue it them, much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſe, ſome in Synods, that beare the name of the church, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he things giuen, and commanded be againſt the kingdome, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ordinance of God, or make religion rediculous, and the word of none effect, as may be ſaid of the Hierarchie, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome ceremonies.</p>
            <p>As namely that in baptiſing an Infant, they ſhould <hi>ſigne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im, vvith the ſigne of the croſſe in token, that he ſhall not be ſhamed to confeſſe the faith of Christ, and manfully to fight <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nder his banner against ſinne, &amp;c.</hi> and yet vvhen he comes page, he is prohibited to contend for that faith againſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minian and popiſh, errours: yea a miniſter is alſo forbidden <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o doe it, though at his ordination he is made to promiſe <hi>to be ready vvith all diligence to baniſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of Biſhops Prieſts, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>and driue away all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rronious, &amp; ſtrange doctrines, contrarie to Gods vvord:</hi> VVhat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ockeries are theſe? And novv in theſe daies of the churches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rouble, &amp; perſecution, haue the Engliſh, that ſtand ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or theſe ſignes, and ceremonies, proued better ſouldiers of Chriſt, in ſuch caſes as that of the Palatinate, and the like, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen they of other churches, that haue them not? or haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey not rather proued vvorſe? Doe they more feare God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re they more obedient to his ordinances, and keepe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hurch more vncorrupt, then thoſe Proteſtants that vveare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſurpleſſes, bovv not to the Altar, nor kneele not vvhen
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:4072:22"/>they receiue? Surely not more, but leſſe. Such a one as Doctor Lambe, or other prophane men, amidſt all their knovvne abhominations, may liue in more peace vvith them, then one, that vvithout iuſt cauſe they call a Puritain. God is much better pleaſed vvhen churches, and their learned defenders, are more in deedes, and leſſe in ſuch ſignes of humaine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention, as are but meere mockeries, and burdens.</p>
            <p>That ancient Biſhops and Synods haue vſed, and ordained theſe, &amp; the like things, is no warrant for them. For you may ſee the caſe of the ancient Biſhops in their ſucceſſions, by the Engliſh, and their moſt learned defenders: vvho (as manie novv liuing haue ſeene) becauſe they receiued not <hi>the loue of the Truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.</note> in matter of the Elderſhip, traditions, and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, but <hi>their</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 29.</note> 
               <hi>feare toward God</hi> hath, in theſe caſes, bene <hi>taught by the precepts of men:</hi> therefore God hath giuen them ouer to beleeue ſome popiſh, and Arminian lies: and becauſe they receiue not the loue of the truth, in thoſe matters of Arminianiſme, wherin alſo their feare toward God is taught by the precepts of men, God muſt needes giue them ouer to ſtronger deluſions, to beleeue vvorſe things, &amp; the vviſdome of their vviſe, and learned men, muſt needes be more, and more hid, and periſhing: and they muſt needes fall more, and more into earthly polecies, practiſes, and factions, to colour, and maintaine vvhat they haue done amiſſe, and to hold vp<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and increaſe their povver againſt parliaments, and all their oppoſers: vvhich is not to preſerue order, but to confound it, nor to be true, but falſe helpers to kings, and States: vvhereby Romiſh religion is more helped, then the Proteſtant, the Houſe of Auſtria, then the houſe of God, the greate vvhore, then the reformed churches, and all true, &amp; effectuall confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracie, vvith thoſe churches, againſt the common enemie, is hindred: for indeed to deſire Romes ouerthrovv, vvere to ſeeke their ovvne, in that vvhich is Romiſh: they can not
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:4072:22"/>truly loue them, that are gouerned by Preſbiters:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.10.</note> for <hi>vvhat communion hath light vvith darknes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence it is that forraigne Proteſtants, vvho, truſting to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he helpe of the Engliſh haue ſuffered for it, and in ſteade of helpe haue ſeene many dangerous diuiſions in Engliſh par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iaments, and counſailes, vvhich could not haue bene ſo car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried avvay, but by the helpe, and counenance of the Biſhops, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay, that theſe euils in England, and all others, that by theſe meanes haue be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> allen the reformed churches, haue ſprung from the Engliſh prelacie, &amp; Hierarchie, vvhich bring forth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch Proteſtants, &amp; Biſhops, &amp; vvhich maintaine a nevvtrall, or mixed religion, partly popiſh, in the Hierarchie, traditions, and ceremonies, maintained vvith moſt zeale, partly of the reformed, in points of faith leſſe regarded, and partly of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minianiſme lately receiued: all vvhich makes them luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvarme Laodiceans, or nevvters, that as much helpe the one ſide, as the other, in treaties, leagues, ſuccours, &amp;c. And ſo the Prelates, vvith their Hierarchie, and traditions, are like to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iuer Euphrates, that ran betvveene Babylon, &amp; her enemies, vvatered both ſides, &amp; hindred the ſurpriſing of her, as theſe muſt needes doe the ſacking of Rome, till their dominion, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iches, that makes them thus corrupt, be taken avvay, &amp; their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>euenues turned to better vſes. And therefore their ſaying againſt vs, that this is Cham like to diſcouer the nakenes of ones Father, or mother,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 6.16. 2 Sam. 6.</note> vvith the Bethſhemites to prie <hi>into the Arke,</hi> vvith Vzzah that offered to ſupport it, to meddle in things that belong not to vs, but to the Biſhops: there muſt be ſuch to preſerue order, and all the other parts of their plea, are plainly a buſed, made meere ſhifts, &amp; mights as vv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll haue ſerued the Papiſts againſt VValdo, Luther &amp; Caluin, as them againſt the Elderſhip. If they vvould ſpeake truth, they might rather ſay, as by <hi>Constantines,</hi> ſo by Queen <hi>Flizabeths</hi> comming to the crovvne, vvith peace entred plentie, &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and vvith them anibition, coueteoſnes, &amp; corruption.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:4072:23"/>So in ſhort time, and by degrees, it fared vvith thoſe ancient Biſhops, their feare tovvard God in matters of their Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, traditions, and ceremonies, began to be taught by the precepts of men: vvith theſe ambition, and coueteouſnes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the church: therefore firſt in theſe, &amp; then in other things, their vviſdome began to be hid, and periſhing, ſo that they could not ſee the miſchiefes follovving dioceſſan, and prouinciall Biſhops.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The church of Rome at that time the Bulvvark, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of dioceſſan Epiſcopacie, vvas not then knovvne to be the <hi>VVhore</hi> ef Babylon, and <hi>mother of fornications:</hi> but for her integritie in other matters, as againſt Arrians, and other hereticks vvas thought the <hi>pillar of truth:</hi> and for the greatnes of her Biſhop not oppoſed by many, but rather applauded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the moſt: therefore fevv or none vvould then ſpeake againſt her cuſtome, and tenets: vvhich indeede made their ovvne Epiſcopall authoritie to be held the more lavvfull; and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, the rather becauſe of the honour &amp; profit, that accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied it: So prone is all mankinde to encline to thoſe vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and be blinded by them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Though it vvere vvithout all true authoritie of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yet cuſtome, and conſent of Synods had eſtabliſhed, and increaſed it, as they alſo did the primacie, and povver of the Pope in the Nicence, Sardean, and other councels: &amp; therefore it vvas thought an hereſie in Aerius to diſſent from them vvhereas the hereſie vvas rather in them that diſſented from the inſtitution, and practiſe of the church in the time of the Apoſtles: but indeed the miſterie of iniquitie could not other vviſe haue vvrought, that the church of Rome ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the great vvhore, and her Biſhop the Antichriſt. For theſe ordinances, that ſet vp dioceſſan Biſhops, Archbiſhops and Patriarchs, vvith many many nevv rites, and ceremonies, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered the greatnes, and authoritie of the Biſhop, and church
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:4072:23"/>of Rome, and ſuch vvas then the cuſtome, and doctrine of that church, implying, that they vvere neceſſarie: therefore it vvas counted Schiſme, and hereſie to hold any thing to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie, though taught in ſcriptures, the name of the church did carrie it againſt all proofes vvhatſoeuer. If any oppoſed, and ſaide, theſe things vvere Ievviſh, heatheniſh. or Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, or tended that vvay, they could not vvant inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall daubers, to quiet or confound them, vvith abuſing ſuch places as that,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.15. Epheſ. 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>If ye bite &amp; deuoure one another, take heede ye be not deuoured one of another. Keepe the vnitie of the Spirit in the bond of peace.</hi> Diſpute not about things indiſterent, but rather obſerue vnitie, and vniformitie, vvith due obedience to the church, to Biſhops, to Synods, and their ordinances: and neuer ſay they are ill carried: be not ſo ſeditious, ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall or peruerſe: they are your guides, and you ſhould be guided, and ruled by them. By theſe, and the like meanes, and deuiſes, they paſſed from errour to errour.</p>
            <p>Euen as at this day in England, the Supporters of the Hier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archie, and Arminianiſme preuaile by the ſame reaſons, by abuſing the ſame, and the like places, and by ſaying, the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Synods ordained Archbiſhops, and Biſhops, and the cuſtome, and doctrine of the church of England doe implie, and teach, that they, and their traditions, and gouernment are neceſſarie, therefore it is ſchiſme, and hereſie to diſſent from them, that is, though you hold vvith the ſcriptures: the name of the church of England muſt carrie it againſt all proofes vvhatſoeuer: and therefore though they vvill not be accounted Papiſts, as thoſe are vvho ſtand for the Pope, yet are they Pontificians, ſuch as maintaine dioceſſan, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinciall Biſhops, &amp; the oppoſers thereof to be ſchiſmaticks and hereticks. For they knovv, that as it vvas of old, ſo at this day, the calling of them hereticks, is (next to povver, cuſtome and humaine conſtitution) the beſt argument to defend their
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:4072:24"/>Hierarchie, and the traditions thereof. For vvhile they ſcoffe at them, and their <hi>Tenets,</hi> and call them hereticks, Puri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ains, &amp; peruerſe Spirits, that labour to proue that the Hierarchie ought to be aboliſhed, &amp; the Elderſhip reſtored, this makes Princes, nobles, miniſters, and people to ſtop their eares, and eyes, againſt all the beſt reaſons, and proofes of Scripture, in theſe caſes, and in like manner to ſcoffe at them.<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 16.14. Iohn 9.29.</note> So the Phariſes derided Chriſt, like as at this day, the greateſt defence of Romiſh religion, is ſcoffing at the Proteſtant faith, calling it hereſie, &amp; them hereticks that profeſſe it: this makes Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Prieſts, and people to looke no further, but to ſtop their eares againſt all proofes, as againſt the Sophiſtrie of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks. VVith this deuiſe alſo hath the church of Rome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed from time to time, and by it ran from one errour to another, till ſhe became full of abhominations, and to haue ſuch povver, that no man durſt vndertake to conuince her. And ſo may the church of England, vvho hath begun ſuch a progreſſe, in ſome popiſh ceremonies, &amp; Arminian errours, vvhich are maintained by practiſes, as beeing ſuch, as they vvill ſuffer no man to diſpute againſt: but vvith povver, and cunning pretences prohibit all from gainſaying her Prelates in any thing,<note n="*" place="margin">2. Cor. 1.24.</note> as the church of Rome did. This is to <hi>haue do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion ouer mens faith,</hi> vvhich the Apoſtles abhorred, ſeeing the truth of God, is in theſe points reuealed, and things <hi>reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led belong to vs,</hi> to vvhome it is giuen to <hi>contend for the faith.</hi> VVhence it muſt needes follovv, that they alſo vvill get a povver to doe, &amp; teach vvhat they liſt, and yet no man ſhall dare to conuince them. For Chriſt ſaith, <hi>He that is vniust is the leaſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 16.10</note> 
               <hi>is vniust alſo in much.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let no man therefore ſay theſe are ſmall differences, that the authoritie of Biſhops ſhould be receiued in them, or that they are matters too high for the people, ſeeing they are not higher then the myſteries of the Trinitie, vvhich being
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:4072:24"/>alſo taught in Scriptures ſhould be held of all, and not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, as theſe are, to open a gap for<note n="*" place="margin">Which is the drift of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ectors and Abettors.</note> poperie to enter. For ſuch euer haue bene, ſuch are, and ſuch muſt needes be the fruit of greatnes in the clergie. And therefore vvhereas ſome ſay, as the church grevv larger, and larger, ſo there might be nevv offices, &amp; officers ordained, hauing greater honour, and more ample iuriſdiction, and command, ouer vvhole countries, and Prouinces, they ſee here the fruits of it, in Rome, and in England. It is not the putting of religious men into the papacie, or into Engliſh Biſhopvvricks, that vvill helpe theſe things, if the callings be of men, and not of God, as is proued in both. For out of this opinion Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt aroſe to his greatnes, and the church of Rome to her authoritie, errour, and tyrannie,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.15</note> and <hi>that vvhich is highly esteemed amongst men is (oft times) abhomination in the ſight of God,</hi> that puniſheth mens inuentions, and preſumptions. VVhich in this caſe vvere verie abſurd. For the church vvas much enlarged in the Apoſtles daies, yet did they not appoint dioceſſan Biſhops, and Archbiſhops:<note place="margin">Act. 14.23 Tit. 1.5.</note> but as churches vvere daily founded in any kingdome, ſo they <hi>ordained them El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and deacons in euery church</hi> or congregation, hauing no other ſpirituall head then Chriſt; nor no other meanes to repr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe errour, and Schiſme, then vvas in the Apoſtles time, to vvit, calling of Synods to reduce doctrine, and diſcipline to that of the Apoſtles. VVhich indeed ſhould be furthered, cheriſhed, and maintained by kings, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, as by nurſing fathers. VVherein all ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thoſe things. <hi>Remoue not the ancient bounds,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 22.28 Eccle. 10.8</note> 
               <hi>vvhich thy Fathers haue ſet. He that breaketh an hedge a Serpent ſhall bite him.</hi> The Inuentours, enlargers, and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of Dioceſſan Epiſcopacie, haue remoued, and broken the bounds, the Apoſtles ſet, and haue planted Dioceſſan, and Prouinciall Biſhops, trees that brought out fruits
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:4072:25"/>accordingly many biting errours haue bene propagated by the great names of Biſhops and Popes, ſuch as Paulus Semo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſateneus, Liberius, Neſtorius, and many others, after the bounds were broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which ſhould haue bin better obſerued. And if in any congregation, by reaſon of the largenes of the pariſh, or the many, and rich people that dvvell in it, ſome miniſters come to better meanes then other, happy man by his lot: that is the greateſt difference, that ought to haue bene betvveene one Paſtor &amp; an other. The choice of miniſters lying moſt in the pariſh, and ſuch miniſters, and Elders, as dvvell neere about them. And this vvay miniſters, and people ſhould haue bene better prouided for, then novv they are, vvhen ſome haue double benefices, Biſhopvvricks, Denaries, comendaes, and in a vvord ſome fevv haue all, though they preach litle, but the moſt haue litle or neuer a vvhit, though they vvould preach, and inſtruct. Therefore vvhereas ſome ſay theſe places are better encouragments to make Schollars ſtuddie, then the paritie of the Puri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ains: vve ſee here that they are rather nurſeries of ſuperſtition, briberie, ſimonie, non reſidencie, idlenes, ambition, and errour, and meere allurements to make men ſtuddie, to maintaine ſuch traditions, and ceremonies as make the vvord of none effect, to get dominion ouer mens faith, and euen to mold religion after the pleaſure of ſuch as can aduance them to thoſe great places: ſo exceedingly doe they corrupt the church. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that hath, and vvill more fully be found of them vvhich Zanchie ſaith of the Hierarchie, &amp; ordinances of the ancient fathers, and councels. * <hi>All things by ſucceſsion of times vver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> brought to an extreame tyrannie and ambition:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zanch. ſides de religio. Chriſtia. cap. 25. See. 12.</note> 
               <hi>vvhich is the reaſon vvhy, by ſo much the neerer, as men approach in theſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of ministers to the ſimplicitie of the Apostles, by ſo much the more ought they to be approued by vs, and vvee iudge th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> men ought to indeauour that things may euery where be brough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:4072:25"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o that order.</hi> All the Reformed Churches hold, and follovv <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he proofes of this opinion.<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.20.</note> Only the Prelates and Doctors of England account them verie ſtrange, and therefore hate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he light in this point. So that God may ſay of them, as of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>phraim, <hi>I haue vvriten to him the greate things of my law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut they vvere counted as a ſtrang thing.</hi> They haue a better <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pinion of their ovvne ordinances, and are better acquainted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vith them: they ſuffer Princes, and people to heare, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>novv them, and all the reaſons they haue for them; but not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he proofes that are for the Elderſhip, though our Lord ſay: He <hi>that is of God, heareth Gods vvords:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.47.</note> 
               <hi>yee therefore heare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem not,</hi> becauſe ye are not of God.<note place="margin">chap. 18.37</note> 
               <hi>Euery one that is of the Truth heareth my voice.</hi> VVherein they are not the more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xcuſable, becauſe theſe or the like things haue bene in ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ort vſed by the ancient churches, or are commanded by Kings &amp; States, vvhen indeed it hath commonly bene, at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſtance of the Biſhops or their faction. It is ſtrang that men, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat thus beare all the ſvvay in the church, rule all things, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uen giue lavves to others, haue no other vvarrant for this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir office, &amp; authority, then cuſtome, Eccleſiaſtical conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on, vvherein themſelues haue bene the Iudges, or the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent, and appointment of Kings. For as to ſuch cuſtome, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onſtitution, that which a learned Author ſaith in a like caſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s vvorthy obſeruation.<note place="margin">Hiſtor. of the counc, of Trent. pag. 18.</note> The impietie of Neſtorius had diuided Chriſt, making two ſonnes, and denying him to be God, who was borne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the bleſſed virgin, the church to inculcate the Catholike truth in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>indes of the faithfull, made often mencion of her in the churches, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vell of the Eaſt, as of the Weſt, with this title, Marie the mother of God. This being inſtituted only for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> honour of Chriſt, was by litle, and litle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ommunicated alſo to the mother, and finally applied to her alone, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herefore when Images began to multiplie, Chriſt was painted as a babe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n his mothers armes, to put vs in minde of the worſhip due vnto him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uen in that age. But in progreſſe of time, it was turned into the worſhip <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the mother, without the ſonne, he remaining as an appendex in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icture. The writers and Preachers, eſpeciallie thoſe that were contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>latiue, caried with the terrent of the vulgar, which is able to doe much
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:4072:26"/>in theſe matters, leauing to mencion Chriſt, inuented with one accord new praiſes, Epithites, and religious ſeruices: In ſo much, that aboute the yeere 1050. a daily office was inſtituted to the bleſſed virgin, diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by ſeuen Canonical howres, in a former which anciently was euer vſed to the honour of the diuine maieſtie, and in the next hundred veers, the worſhip ſo increaſed, that it came to the height, euen to attribute that vnto her, which the Scriptures ſpeake of the diuine wiſdome. And amongſt theſe inuented nouities, this was one, her totall exemption from originall ſinne. Yet this remained only in the breaſts of ſome few priuate men, hauing no place in Eccleſiaſticall ceremonies, or amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the learned. He ſhevveth, hovv it vvas oppoſed, and yet after came to be receiued by the induſtrie of Scotus, and other Franciſcans, vvhich is a Storie too lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g for this place. From this part of the narration, wee ſee hovv many euils ſprung from that ancient inuention of painting Chriſt as a babe in his mothers armes, vvhich it may be, did litle hurt at the firſt, and vvas beheld, as a thing indifferent, vvith litle or no offence, &amp; accounted tollerable, if allovved by authoritie. The inuentors might meane as litle harme in it, yet doubtles the inuention, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovvance gaue occaſion of all theſe euils, &amp; vvas ſome breack of the ſecond comandement; as vvomen that friſſe their hair, paint, or lay open their naked breaſts are occaſions of luſt, &amp; breake the commandement, &amp; ſuch precepts, as require mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie, though they doe not theſe things on purpoſe to make men fornicators, but for faſhion ſake, to get huſbands, or the like reaſon. At this day there is ſuch an Image of the virgin reedified, &amp; beautified at the croſſe in cheape ſide. Beſides En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh Papiſts, diuers Spaniards, &amp; others, haue bene obſerued to vvorſhip it: and therefore neither the ancient cuſtome of this inuention, nor any conſtitution allowing it, nor the little hurt it did at the firſt, or novv doth to many, can ſerue to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the Rulers that ſuffer it. For vvee ſee many kings are bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for ſuffering the high places, vvhich ſome time vvere litle frequented, or at leaſt not by many. Smal faults &amp; errours make vvay for greater. It may be the inuentors and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of dioceſſan Biſhops, &amp; ſom Romiſh ceremonies meant
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:4072:26"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s litle hurt at the firſt, as any of theſe; yet ſeeing they haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one, doe, &amp; may doe ſo much hurt, it is a great fault to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aine or ſuffer them. The Ieſuits know, that the maintenance of them, and ſuppreſſing of bookes againſt them, are notable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nductions to nevvtralitie, luke vvarmnes, ignorance, errour, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd poperie, as they finde in many Arminians, and pontifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns: &amp; further, that no Proteſtant church in the vvorld hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o handſom a cloake for a church Papiſt, Spaniſh, or Romiſh, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s theſe ſerue for. And yet theſe, as all the errours of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh church, being once receiued, haue bene maintained by men of great pretie, &amp; knovvledge in other things. VVho are thought to haue more knovvledge, holines, &amp; deuotion then ſome franciſcans, that maintaine theſe errours about the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed virgin, &amp; others of poperie. The deuil, &amp; all corrupt men, hauing once broached any errour, euer get ſome of the moſt religious, and learned to defend it, or at leaſt, that it is a thing indifferent or tollerable: thus the beginnings of Dioceſſan Biſhops, and Romiſh ceremonies, ſome primacie in the Pope, Images in the churches to a religious vſe, and the like, being begun vvith ſmaller digreſſions from the truth, haue gained ſome to defend them, as things indifferent, and tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, vvho vvere reckoned, &amp; oft vvere, men of great knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and pierie in other matters and then theſe errours, and abuſes, being thus defended, grevv greater, and more intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. So the Biſhops in England, hauing gotten ſome men to ſubſcribe, that are verie learned, &amp; religious, they then get them alſo to defend their Hierarchie, traditions, and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies: vvhich doctrine they knovv, vvill be beſt receiued at ſuch mens hand, as vvee haue of late ſeene in Doctor <hi>Burges,</hi> and others, much graced by the Biſhops, vvho among themſelues alſo haue ſome that are, and others, that ſeeme to be verie religious in many things. But vvee ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that theſe are but men, that engaged a litle in any cauſe, are ſubiect to fall farther into it; that gifts or hopes of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:4072:27"/>preferment blind the eies of the vviſe, that the church of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me could neuer haue gained her cauſe in ſo many things, if ſhe had not had the helpe of men, eſteemed as religious, and learned; that ſhe could neuer vvant of this ſort, vvho had ſuch revvards for her champions, &amp; ſuch povver to ſuſpend, and ſilence, the oppoſers; no more can the Biſhops.</p>
            <p>The 34.<note place="margin">Art. 34.</note> Article ſaith thus, <hi>It is not neceſſary that traditions, &amp; ceremonies be in all places one or vtterly like, for at all times, they haue bene diuers, and may be changed according to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of countries times, and mens manners, ſo that nothing be ordained, against Gods vvord.</hi> I anſvvere, in ſome caſes this may be admitted. For the Apoſtle vvould not haue a man praying, to be couered in the church, and in thoſe hot coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, if any that might wel endure to be bareheaded in praier,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.4. &amp;c.</note> as the moſt might, ſhould haue vvorne a night cap, or the like thing in the church, it had bene as greate an euill in him as if he had vvorne a hart: yet in ours, being a much colder countrie, the church, vvith good reaſon, allovveth ſuch to vveare night caps in time of praier, as can not vvith ſafety of their health be vncouered ſo long. God requires not the death or danger of his creatures in ſuch caſes. In Muſcouie, Svvede, and ſome colder Climates, men are ſo bitten vvith froſt, that they are conſtrained to keepe ſomvvhat on their heads. Here neceſſitie requireth, that the ceremonie be not the ſame, nor in ſome old or ſick body, that is not able to kneele all the time of praier. But vvhat neceſſitie is there for the croſſe in Baptiſme, the ſurpleſſe, copes, or kneeling at the Sacrament, which vvere not vſed in the age of the Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, are but meere mockeries, make the vvord of none effect, and haue bene ſo much abuſed to idollatrie, as the Image of the bleſſed virgin? Becauſe the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.40.</note> 
               <hi>Let all things be done decently, and in order,</hi> therefore ſome infer, the church or the magiſtrate may ordaine theſe, and the like. A fooliſh
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:4072:27"/>inference, that ſerues as vvell for the Paplſts, and their trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries, pretended to belong to decencie, &amp; order, as for them. For hovv is there more decencie, and order, in theſe things then vvas in the time of the Apoſtles, or is novv in the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med churches? The Apoſtle ſpeakes of decencie and order, vvhereby they ſhould be the better Chriſtians, the vvomen being couered, the men vncouered in time of praier: the men ſpeaking in a knovvne tongue, and one after another, not confuſedly, the vvomen keeping ſilence in the church: of theſe, and the like, he ſaith, Let all things be done decently, and in order. But vvhat better Chriſtians are men for the croſſe in baptiſme, for the ſurpleſſe, and kneeling at the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament? vvhat more decencie, and order in the ſurpleſſe, then in a ſhirt of haire, a Ieſuits cloake a friers vvhite roabe, a Capuchins gray govvne, &amp; hood, or the rope vvherevvith he girds himſelfe? vvhat more decencie, and order in the croſſe in baptiſme, then in the croſſe that hangs at the friers girdle? in kneeling at the receiuing of the bread, then in kneeling at the feete of a Prieſt in confeſſion, before a croſſe, or Image, or at their receiuing of the hoſt? vvhat more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, and order in dioceſſan, &amp; prouinciall Biſhops, Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours, Deanes, and Archdeacons, and their courts, and proceedings, then in thoſe of the church of Rome, the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals Generals, and Canoniſts, ſaue in the degrees of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition and impietie?</p>
            <p>That place indeed giues vvarrant in ſome caſes, as touching the time, and place of Gods vvorſhip, and needefull ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies therein. That on the Lords day, it ſhould begin about 8. or 9. in the morning, and end before noone, and begin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine about tvvo, becauſe men in many places haue far to church, and the daies being ſhort, muſt haue time to goe to, and fro, and to dine. That though in the primatiue church, the place vvere oft in mens houſes, a barne, or in the feildes:
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:4072:28"/>yet novv it is fit to haue a Temple, vvhere it may be had, or a place ſet apart for that vſe. In the reformed churches one rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the chapters, &amp; begins the Pſalmes, theſe things are done in better order, when they are committed to one, vvho com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly hath a good voice, and ſkill in tuning: and if it vvere not ſo, there vvould be ſome diſorder. Order is alſo taken for the moſt decent comming to the table of the Lord, gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of almes, keeping ſilence, and vſing decent geſture in the church. Novv if theſe things were not altogether thus in the primatiue church: yet the alteration in ceremonie, is litle or nothing, and rather to things decent, and neceſſarie, then to hurtfull, &amp; vnproffitable. But this can not be ſaid of the croſſe in baptiſme, the ſurpleſſe, or kneeling at the Sacrament, much leſſe of the Epiſcopall povver, and Hierarchie, theſe are not things neceſſarie, but vnproffitable, &amp; hurtfull, not better but vvorſe. In England verie many Miniſters, &amp; ſome that haue ſmal meanes, weare beuer hats of great price (which not many yeeres ſince vvere vvorne of none but Princes) alſo caſſocks, &amp; dublits of Sattin, cloakes faced, &amp; ſome lined vvith veluer, &amp; pluſh: their vviues alſo goe in looſe govvnes of ſilke, beuer hats, fannes in their hands, and many other vanities. It is true that both the one, and the other may goe neare, &amp; cleane, not fordid, and naſtie, but yet not thus coſtly, and vainly: vvherin they making litle conſcience, are the eaſier induced to thinke of tvvo liuings to maintaine it, and a coach to boote, &amp; then of being made Doctors, Deanes, &amp; Biſhops, and ſomtimes at the inſtance of their vviues, becauſe they vvould haue place; yea to buye theſe honours, and benefices, or flatter for them: vvherin mens mindes are ſeldome ſatisfied, but rather more enflamed, and corrupted: being Doctors they vvould haue a prebendarie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or another liuing, and then be Deanes: hauing a Denarie, they vvould haue a Biſhopvvrick, hauing gotten that, they aime at a better: and to attaine them, they are ſtill
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:4072:28"/>forced to flatter, bribe, bid, &amp; outbid, as in a market, or vvhere things are ſold by the candle, or at an outcrie, to the extreme ſhame of the Chriſtian profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. So that if theſe great places vvere lavvfull, yet almoſt nothing is left to deſert, or free election: commonly all goes by money, corruption, or friends in the court, ſuch as the Duke, vvho ſtrengthen their faction, by them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Hence follovves idlenes, and non reſidence, luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvarmnes, and temporiſing: they vvho make no conſcience of ſuch th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngs can not but be blind in others, the ſpirit of God forſakes them, they are the more eaſely induced to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Hierarchie, and ceremonies, to let in Arminianiſme, ſome kinde of poperie, or other corruption in doctrine, and diſcipline at the pleaſure of ſuch as can aduance them, or at leaſt to vvinke at ſuch proceedings: and thus they become nouriſhers of poperie, and the ſteps to it: for our Sauiour ſaith, <hi>He that is not vvith me is againſt me;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 12.30</note> 
               <hi>and he that ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth not vvith me ſcattereth abroade.</hi> But indeed an euill tree can not bring foorth good fruite. Theſe great places in the Hierarchie being not of God, but of men, ſuch muſt needes, be the fruits of them. If the church ſeeing theſe euils ſpring from pride, ambition, &amp; coueteouſnes, ſhould ordaine a meane to all, in apparell, and yeerely maintenance and ſuch other things, like that in the reformed churches, doubtles ſuch an ordma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vvere to be obeied, the church hath povver to doe it, not ſimplie, &amp; abſolutely by any authoritie giuen it in all things, that they pleaſe to call indifferent, but in things thus neceſſarie, &amp; agreable to the vvord of Gods, vvhich for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids ſuch coſtly apparell, and lordſhip in them, &amp; commands them to be graue, and enſamples to the flocks: the churches authoritie is nothing but in theſe caſes, and ſuch others of diſcipline as is aboue named. In all other, Chriſt is the only lavvgiuer of his Church, as the Sole huſband thereof, and Lord of the familie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:4072:29"/>
Not to inſiſt vpon other things, vvhat neceſſarie vſe is there, of Cathedral churches, of vvhich, ſome make ſo much religion, to haue them reedefied? In that of London, the vpper, and leſſe part is only vſed in ſeruice. Some of thoſe greate fabricks haue bene, and might be vvell imploied as colledgiate churches, for reading of lectures, and preſeruing of puritie in doctrine, good manners, and learning: things of this nature doe indeed make them ſomvvhat vvorthy the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing. The greateſt Temples in the reformed churches are put to good vſe, but vvhere there is not ſuch vſe, there it is not vvorth the coſt.<note place="margin">Pleſſes myſt. of iniquit. progreſ. 24.</note> Mounſieur du Pleſſes obſerueth that vvhen religion, and doctrine began to be corrupted, that they might couer it, and ſee me no leſſe religious, they fell to buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Temples, and Altars, to preſſe deuoute geſtures, cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, &amp;c. euen ſo the Biſhops, that vvant zeale againſt poperie, Arminianiſme non reſidencie, and ſuch errours, and abuſes, as are crept into the church, flatter ſuch friends, and ſupporters of them, as are mighty, or able to defend, &amp; reward them, and in the meane time, to ſeeme no leſſe religious, make greate religion of deuoute geſtures, building, repairing, and adoring of Temples in both vvhich, the Papiſts exceede them: and as he ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">Pleſſes vbi ſupra.</note> 
               <hi>The vvorſer ſort of men are euer moſt ſpendfull in ſuch things to ſhadow, and obſcure the memorie of their euill acts.</hi> It is true, that many vvho vvorſhip in ſpirit, and truth, and are zealous that doctrine may be preſerued in the purity the Apoſtles left it, are yet too neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in deuoute geſture in praier, that ſome grovv too familiar, and ſauc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e vvith God: this is ill, but the other is much vvorſe, vvhen men ſeeke the outvvard, neglect due preaching, and hearing, the defence of the truth, &amp; cauſe of God, in ſuch caſes as that of the Palatinate, the Rochellers, and the like, or flatter their falle friends, and betraiers, ſuch as the Duke, &amp;c. for vvhile thus the true church of God,<note place="margin">Mat. 23.23.</note> the liuing ſtones and Temples,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:4072:29"/>vvherein God dvvels, are ſpoiled and vvaſted, ſuch mens cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for bodely geſtures, &amp; building of Temples, is but tithing of mint, and anniſe, and leauing the vveightier matters vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ared for, like hypocriticall Phariſes. Yet vvho ſees not that theſe are the chiefe things the Biſhops looke after? vvho in the meane time thinke it ſufficient, that Synods, and kings haue eſtabliſhed their authoritie.</p>
            <p>It is true that Solomon iuſtly depoſed Abiathar the Prieſt,<note place="margin">1. King. 2.27. chap. 25.13 2 Chro. 17.6.7.</note> and put Zadock in his roome, that <hi>Aſa remoued his mother from being Queene, becauſe ſhe had made an idole,</hi> vvhich he deſtroied, as Hezechiah did the braſen ſerpent, vvhen it vvas abuſed to idolatrie: that Ichoſhaphat, and Ioſiah put downe idollatrie, reformed the church, and cauſed the vvord of God to be duly taught: That Chriſtian Kings, as <hi>nurſing fathers</hi> haue great authority in like caſes: but all this is, as vvas ſaid of Synods, in things neceſſarie, as reformation of abuſes ſupreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing errours, aboliſhing of idollatrie, and ſuperſtitious rites, and gouernments, reeſtabliſhing a preaching miniſtrie, and Elders, and ordaining ordinances, and ceremonies, ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, as thoſe aboue mencioned: That God vvill require it of them, if they doe not looke after theſe things. But for the Hierarchie, and popiſh ceremonies, ſo hurtfull, to proue that they may be maintained, I hope they vvill not ſay,<note place="margin">1. King. 11 2. King. 16 10.</note> Salomon built the high places, Ieroboam ſet vp Calues, Ahaz <hi>ſaw an Altar</hi> at Damaſcus, and made Vrijah the Prieſt build ſuch a one, ſo prone are the clergie to thinke the vvill of the Prince a ſufficient vvarrant, that any king of Iſrael, or Iudah did what he liſt in religion,<note place="margin">2. Chro. 22 34.</note> that among the reft <hi>Ahaziah vvalked in the vvaies</hi> of the houſe of Ahab: for after the death of his father <hi>they, &amp; his mother were his counſellers to his deſtruction.</hi> They ſhould rather put the higher povvers in minde of that, <hi>vvhy tempt ye God, to put a yoke vpon the necks of the Diſciples,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 15.10.</note> 
               <hi>vvhich neither our fathers, nor vvee are able to it beare?</hi> The
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:4072:30"/>King of Kings would not doe it, but after he had finiſhed his Teſtament,<note place="margin">Reu. 2, 24.</note> he ſaith, <hi>I will put vpon you none other burden;</hi> and ſhall men then preſume that they may doe it, if they can get kings to authoriſe them? Kings ſhould remember that Chriſt is ſet vpon the <hi>holy hill of Sion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note> as the only<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 33.22.</note> King, and lavvgiuer of his church in matters of religion: in regard vvhereof it is ſaid, <hi>Be vviſe now therefore, o ye kings: be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed ye Iudges of the earth. Serue the Lord vvith feare, and reioyce vvith trembling. Kiſſe the Sonne least he be angrie:</hi> as if he ſaid, ſhevv your ſubiection, and loue to him, in ſetting vp Gods throne, and ordinances, not Satans. VVhere any Eccleſiaſtical povver, and dominion is beſides, and againſt his ordinances, there hath Satan his throne, though in ſome go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernments, &amp; orders more pernicious, then in others: among the Papiſts, in Popes, Cardinals, Ieſuits, Regulars, &amp; Biſhops. In the Franciſcans, or Capuchins leſſe then in the Ieſuits: yet hath he it, as vvell in the beſt order of them, as in Mahume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, or any other vvherein it is vvorſt. If Engliſh Biſhops haue a povver beſides, and againſt the ordinances of God, &amp; that is pernicious to his kingdome, Satan hath his throne in them, though not in ſo deſperate a manner as in others.</p>
            <p>It helpes not to ſay, that many of them ſtriue to doe God ſeruice in many things For ſo doe diuers in all thoſe orders of the Papiſts, and ſo far as they can doe it vvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the ſafety of their religion, and order: but caſt their crovvnes ordinances, ceremonies, tradi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions, and rules at the feete of Chriſt Ieſus, to haue them tried, and iudged by the vvord, they vvill no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no more vvill the Biſhops. VVhen I conſider hovv vveake their vſurped and tyrannicall title is, I am amaſed that as yet, no Engliſh Biſhop euer did it. Yet vvhen I remember againe that the Scripture ſaith: <hi>Gifts blind the eies of the vviſe:</hi> that our Lord ſaith.<note place="margin">Luk. 16.</note> 
               <hi>No man can ſerue two maisters: ye can not ſerue
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:4072:30"/>God and Mammon. His ſeruants ye are to vvhome ye obey:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> then I vvonder the leſſe, I maruaile not that they doe not beleeue theſe things: becauſe indeed our Sauiour ſaith to ſuch men, <hi>How can ye beleeue vvhich receiue honour one of another,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 5.44.</note> 
               <hi>and ſeeke not the honour, that commeth f om God only?</hi> and of ſuch men: <hi>If any man doe his vvill, he ſhall know of the doctrine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 7.17.</note> 
               <hi>vvhether it be of God or noe.</hi> Theſe and their de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enders can not v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell knovv, becauſe they are not vvilling to knovv it, much leſſe ſo to doe it, as to be reformed by it. They are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to holde to the Hierarchie, becauſe they haue ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, or for the honour, proffit, or peace they haue, or may haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y it, or vnder it, &amp; vvithout vvhich, as things are they knovv <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot hovv to liue, much leſſe to preache, and doe good Novv <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he great and mightie God <hi>the father of lights,</hi> vvith vvhome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> no variablenes, and from vvhome <hi>euery good, and perfit gift <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>roceedeth:</hi> giue them, and vs all the grace,<note place="margin">Luk. 9.</note> that <hi>denying our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elues,</hi> our ovvne affections, vviſdoms, proffits, earthly ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inations, vanities, and delights, vvee may become true Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ples, and follovvers of Chriſt, ſuch as truly ſeeke the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome of God, <hi>and the righteouſnes thereof,</hi> that by his mercie vvee may once come to ſee that ioyfull day,<note place="margin">Reuel. 19.</note> vvherein that bleſſed acclamation ſhall be heard, <hi>Alleluia: For the Lord God omnipotent reigneth.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:4072:31"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <list>
               <item>PAg. <hi>1.</hi> line <hi>20.</hi> for to reade the.</item>
               <item>Pag. <hi>2</hi> line <hi>23.</hi> for hath read hath bin. lin <hi>32.</hi> art reade art.</item>
               <item>Pag. <hi>12.</hi> line <hi>22.</hi> for Ovid. And in an.</item>
               <item>Pag. <hi>23.</hi> for the vvith, reade vvith the.</item>
               <item>Pag. <hi>29.</hi> for in like, reade vvho in like.</item>
               <item>Pag. <hi>41.</hi> line <hi>7.</hi> for ſended, reade tended.</item>
               <item>Pag. <hi>45.</hi> the last line for terrent, read torrent.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:4072:31"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
